[Music]
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome to the Oscar video show.
Today we are discussing history. We are
discussing Indian history as well as
world history. I'll take questions that
you all have asked in the comments.
Before we do that do that as always
let's see who all is there on the live
chat. Let me greet some of you as many
as of you as I can.
I can see Sasmit, Beneat, Bonjour,
Zodiac Cycle, Animesh, Namaste, Happy
Diwali. Happy Diwali to everybody.
Um Chat DSP, Happy Dhanteras. Thank you
and same to everybody else. Freedom from
outcome is here from Canada. Ankita G,
welcome. Thank you very much. Happy
Dhanteras to you as well. Feel strong
man, Pawan Shetty, Shetty, Ayush Singh,
Pranam, Avinash, injured soccer player
from Ontario in Canada,
uh Bruce Wayne, IPK_1S,
Namaskaram, Vladimir Putin, Jai Shri
Ram, Avinash, Bruce Wayne, Sanna,
Apoorva,
Apoorva, Anupama,
Krishna Raghunath from the Suriname is
Netherlands. Vishpala, Namaste. I'm
autistic. Uh
Animesh, Ankita, Pratyush,
uh Ayush Singh, I'm a painter.
Uh Gautami, Happy Diwali. Vishpala,
Namaste. Aryansh Rai Saxena, Parth
Prajapati,
Apoorva Anupama, once again, Roshan,
Roshan Baker, Krishna, Beneat, Gautami,
Vishnu Mohanan, Happy Dhanteras. Uh Jai
Dixit, Jai Dixit, Pratyush, Fireball is
traveling.
Anant Pai, Baron Zemo India,
uh Tushar Kalburgi Kalburgi, Shubha
Deepavali, Gaurav Sarkar, Geopolitical
Dubai from Indore, good evening. Jai
Dixit, Bruce Wayne,
Sasmit,
Who else do we have? Krishna, Abhishek
Gurjar, Nikesh Dahal,
uh Anahita, Pranam,
Aniruddha Godbole, Happy Diwali. Ananta
Subramanian, hello. Alisha B,
Namaskaram.
Krishna says, Krishna, okay. And
Abhishek Gurjar, Nikesh Dahal, once
again,
desperately wants to visit India. Well,
you are always welcome. Please do come.
You're welcome. Uh Vamsi Kalam, Naman
Arora, Karan Yadav, and warrior,
and everyone else. All right, okay,
let's get going with the questions. I'll
take as many questions as I can over the
next couple of hours.
Let's see what questions we have.
Let us begin with a question about
Hannibal Barca. Napoleon Singh Shekhawat
says, "Who was Hannibal Barca?
How did he destroy the Romans?
And how far did he stretch his empire?"
Hannibal Barca was born in Carthage,
which is present-day Tunisia. Let's take
a look at the map to understand what
part of the world we are dealing with.
We're dealing with North Africa.
So, let's go to the map
and visit this location virtually.
So, we're going to North Africa, we go
to Africa, northern Africa, this this
smallish, reasonably smallish nation
called Tunisia.
And if we go to the capital city Tunis,
well,
um where is the location of Carthage?
Carthage?
It's somewhere around Tunis if I recall
correctly.
Let's zoom in further.
Let's zoom in further. Okay, now we are
talking. Now we are dealing Okay, so
this is the ancient port of Carthage,
the Punic ports of Carthage.
Uh and and that still exists as you can
see and there's the archaeological
remains of the city of Carthage and then
you will also have a lot of Roman
uh presence
whose archaeological remains are very
much in evidence in Tunisia and North
Africa overall.
So, that's the region we're talking
about and as you can see it's not really
very far away from Italy,
right? Here we have Italy, which was
part of the Roman Empire. It was the
well, it was the seat of the Roman
Empire out of which governed out of
Rome.
So, Hannibal Barca was born in Carthage,
which is present-day essentially uh the
city of Tunis,
Tunisia. All right? So, that's the first
thing we have to understand about
Hannibal Barca. He was born in Carthage.
So, he was a Carthaginian general.
He was a warrior. He was a general.
And he is considered to be one of the
greatest, most brilliant military
commanders in world history.
He is still remembered for his
incredible tactics, incredible
strategies, and the fact that he nearly
brought the Roman Empire down.
The It was not the Roman Empire at the
time. It was the Roman Republic at that
time. He nearly brought the Roman
Republic to collapse
during a period of time called the
Second Punic War. His father had fought
the First Punic War. Okay? So, we're
talking about the 3rd century BC over
here.
So, Hannibal was the son of
another general whose name was Hamilcar
Barca, who had fought against Rome in
the First Punic War.
And in the First Punic War, Carthage had
been defeated. It had suffered a
humiliating defeat and it had and and
the Romans had imposed very harsh, very
humiliating terms on Carthage.
Uh and this motivated Hannibal Barca to
take revenge against Rome. Kind of what
you see between the First and the Second
World Wars. That sort of thing. Very
similar.
So, when Hannibal was a child, he swore
an oath
of vengeance, of eternal enmity against
Rome against Rome. And he swore that he
would make he would punish Rome for the
humiliation that it had imposed on
Carthage.
So, the Second Punic War starts with
Hannibal
I think attacking Spain.
His It was then called Iberia, which was
the one of the easternmost parts of
Europe, southeastern Europe, and it was
a Roman possession, not quite at the
time, but that's where he starts. Okay?
So, he crosses the sea, he attacks
Spain, he gets a foothold in Spain, and
then what he does, Hannibal, is
something extraordinary.
He conducted one of the most
extraordinary military maneuvers in
European history. He crossed the Alps,
the mountains. Okay? With tens of
thousands of soldiers, of troops, and
also war elephants.
And then he achieved uh
a succession, a series of of victories
against the Romans. So, there were like
multiple battles that he fought and he
defeated the Romans in them in those
battles and then it all culminated with
the Battle of Cannae.
The Battle of Cannae was uh one of the
most devastating defeats that Rome ever
suffered.
Uh Hannibal's armies,
they killed between 50,000
Romans in a single day, soldiers.
Uh entire families, entire bloodlines
were extinguished. It was an absolute
disaster for Rome and Rome came on the
on the on the verge
of essentially entirely falling
to to Hannibal.
But then the Romans
adopted different strategies. They they
adopted the strategy of shying away from
a battle with the with Hannibal and they
kind of kept Rome out of his hands.
And eventually eventually they were able
to rebuild strength, the Romans.
Um
And
and then what what Scipio Africanus, the
Roman general, did is that he invaded
North Africa.
And that's what had to bring Hannibal
back to Africa. He had to go back to
Africa to defend now. Instead of playing
offense, he had to now start playing
defense.
Um and that's how it went and eventually
uh so
So, that's the deal about Hannibal.
He was a
brilliant general. He brought the the
Roman Republic to the brink of disaster,
of of annihilation. And uh
he is regarded as one of the greatest
generals in in world history.
Incredible tactical brilliance,
incredible strategic strategic
brilliance. His his campaigns are
studied in military academies even
today, right?
Uh and so eventually the Roman general
Scipio Africanus invaded North Africa.
This forced Hannibal to return to North
Africa and there he's playing defense
and he eventually suffered a a defeat in
a battle against Scipio Africanus and
that
put an end to Carthage's ambitions of
destroying Rome.
Uh
And what was the eventual fate of
Hannibal Barca?
So, after the Second Punic War, he kind
of became a statesman in North Africa in
Carthage and he was the advisor to
various kings and so on. And eventually
the Romans started exerting more and
more influence in Carthage. And sometime
in the 2nd Century BC, Hannibal faced a
choice. Either be captured by the Romans
or escape the capture
by killing himself. So, he took his own
life. And that's the story of Hannibal
Barca essentially.
Um so, he was not an emperor. He did not
have an empire. He was a He was a
general. He was fighting on behalf of
Carthage and he did not get sufficient
assistance from Carthage. Otherwise, he
would have uh perhaps been able to
totally defeat Rome, right? So, maybe
there were elements of rivalry elements
of elements elements of jealousy
elements of fear back home this guy may
become too powerful and he may take over
Carthage and become an emperor instead
of just being general and so on and that
contributed to the eventual demise of
Carthage itself. Eventually.
Right. So, that's about Hannibal Barca.
Very
I mean, a really
renowned general and a very interesting
person in world history.
Next question is by Saloni Mishra. Why
did the IRA assassinate Mountbatten?
Who is Mountbatten or what is the IRA?
So, the IRA is the Irish Republican
Army.
Uh they they are or they used to be
um a freedom fighting force that was
fighting against the British occupation
of Ireland, which still continues in
Northern Ireland. Northern Ireland is
still occupied by the British, by the
way.
So, the IRA were fighting the British
occupation through violent means, not
through the stupid ahimsa nonsense,
but through violent means. Because
through ahimsa, you can only achieve
vassalage.
Through violent means, you can actually
defeat your oppressors and and you know,
ensure that there is full victory. So,
the IRA were fighting the British
occupation of Ireland. Okay? Now, coming
to Mountbatten. Lord Mountbatten was the
last was the first governor general of
independent of of uh
not independent India, but uh dominion
status India. So, 15th August 1947 is
dominion status day. Okay? You have been
misled that it is Independence Day. It
is dominion status day. India became a
dominion of the British Empire on the
15th of August 1947.
And Mountbatten was made the first
governor general of dominion status
India.
Now, who was this guy, Mountbatten? He
was a German. Well, at least he was of
German origin. His family originated in
Germany.
And their their actual name was
Battenberg,
not Mountbatten. It was Battenberg.
Um and during the First World War, when
there were very strong anti-German
sentiments in in England in Britain, the
Battenberg family changed their name to
Mountbatten. See, the word berg, b e r
g, berg like iceberg, it means it means
a mountain. Iceberg means ice mountain.
It means mountain in German in the
German language, berg. So, Battenberg
was then translated into English to make
it Mountbatten and they became the
Mountbatten family.
So, uh Lord Mountbatten, he's his elder
sister, she had a son who went on who
whose name was Philip.
And
Philip's father died at
when Philip was young and Mountbatten,
his uncle his uncle, became kind of a
father figure in his life.
And he took care of Philip and he
mentored Philip, right? You need a
strong male presence in your life. So,
Mountbatten became that male presence
and he eventually introduced Philip
to Princess Elizabeth.
And prince and and Philip ended up
marrying Princess Elizabeth and he
became um
and and Elizabeth went on to become the
Queen of England, right?
So, that's the story of Philip.
Uh so, Mountbatten was a very uh
prominent figure
in the royal family of England. Even
Elizabeth's family had German ancestry
and so on. So, essentially the Germans
were ruling England. And they changed
their their name to the House of Windsor
around the same time that Mount the
Battenbergs changed their surname to
Mountbatten. That sort of thing. So,
Lord Mountbatten was a very prominent
figure of the royal family of England.
Okay? He was like a father kind of a
father to Prince Philip, who was the
husband of the Queen of England. So,
very prominent member of the family.
So, the IRA were fighting for
independence of Ireland. And they used
non-vi- they used violent means and they
wanted to make a statement. So, they
took out Mountbatten when he was on a
boat in a lake somewhere. Okay? And they
they planted a they planted a bomb on on
on the boat and that explosion took out
Mountbatten. I suppose his body would
never have been recovered
properly.
And that was the fate of of Mountbatten.
So, that's why the IRA assassinated uh
Mountbatten, Lord Mountbatten, because
they they wanted a prominent target, a
very high-ranking target, a target that
was very closely closely associated with
the royal family, kind of a member of
the royal family itself,
right? To bring
uh to to to first of all send a message
to the occupiers, to the oppressors that
you know, we can target any of you. And
secondly, to bring more publicity to the
fact that Ireland was under British
occupation, right? And uh it still is
under British occupation, but today the
IRA has gone to sleep
for whatever reason.
All right? So, that's the deal. That's
why the IRA assassinated Mountbatten.
Amisha Bishnoi says, "Who were the
Mycenaeans
and how did they differ from the
popularized ancient Greeks?"
Okay. Let us first go to the map and
discover the geography that we are
discussing. Okay? Then we will deal with
the historical issue of who are the
Mycenaeans etc. So, let's go to the map.
Here's is the map. Now, we zoom
westwards from India. We cross the
Persian Gulf. We cross uh
the the far the the
what do they call this? The Middle
Middle East? Yeah? Or West Asia?
And then we are into the Mediterranean
Sea.
So, we are talking about Greece over
here, right? Greece is slightly
eastwards of Rome. You have to cross the
Adriatic Sea and then you are in in
Greece.
So, we're talking about an ancient
race of Greeks essentially, so to say,
the Mycenaean Greeks. So, who were these
Mycenaeans and how did they differ from
the later Greeks? So, we have to look at
some chronological issues here. So, this
is the region we're dealing with. Now,
first of all,
even before the Mycenaeans, there was
something called the Minoans.
The Minoans, they uh lived in this
island called Kriti Crete. It's it's
called Kriti today or it it was called
Crete. Okay? So, the Minoans lived on
this island called Crete about between
3,000 BC to about about 1,000 BC. From
3,000 to 1,000 BC, about 2,000 years,
the Minoan civilization lived on this
small island. And one interesting fact
about the Minoans before I proceed
further with this uh with this topic,
in in Minoan, they have discovered
paintings of a certain kind of monkey
that
completely stumped historians. What is
this monkey? We have never seen this
monkey anywhere in this region. Okay?
And it turned out to be the langur,
which is a monkey that's found in India.
So, the Minoans,
they apparently had langurs
about 4,000 5,000 years before today
during the period of time which we call
in India the Indus Saraswati Sindhu
Saraswati phase of our history.
So, it looks like the Sindhu Saraswati
era Indians had contacts with Minoan.
Maybe we were tra- trading with Minoan
or maybe Minoan was trading with us or
whichever way it was. But Minoan had
access to Indian langurs and they
painted Indian langurs uh on on certain
frescoes on the walls of temples and
buildings and stuff.
So, that's Minoan.
So, the Minoans were the what you could
say what you would call the oldest uh
civilization in the region. Were they
Greeks? Were they non-Greeks? Well,
that's a different story. They clearly
were most likely Indo-European. And
their civilization takes a sudden
downfall about 1500 BC, which probably
has something to do with this island
here,
which is today called Santorini. It was
called Thera in the past. And as you can
see, if you look at the satellite image,
it's kind of circular weirdly
because this used to be a gigantic
ginormous volcano
and it exploded somewhere around 1500 BC
and it most likely caused
a complete utter catastrophic disaster,
which hastened the fall of the Minoan
civilization. Okay? So, that's 1500 BC,
but Minoan starts about 3,000 BC and it
ends about 1,000 BC. Now, coming to the
main question, the Mycenaeans. The
Mycenaeans
were a group of Indo-European people
who arrived in Greece
around
2,000 BC. Maybe maybe after 2,000 BC,
maybe 1900 BC.
Indo-Europeans
who
arrived in Greece, let's say around 1900
BC.
So, that's more than a thousand years
before after the beginning of the of the
Minoan civilization.
And the Mycenaeans, they were they they,
you know,
they spread across various islands and
various parts of Greece.
So, it's like Greece had its own
Aryan invasion, migration, whatever you
want to call it.
Okay, Indo-Europeans.
Those were the Mycenaeans.
And uh so
and and they had this
so
they spoke
what is called what is considered to be
the oldest version of the Greek
language. And their script is called
Linear A or something. Linear A most
likely. That's the script that they
used.
Um
and
and it is and and the Mycenaean
phase of Greek history ends
catastrophically around 1100 BC.
Okay, around 1100 BC. What happened
around in 1100 BC?
The Trojan War happened around 1100 BC.
And where was Troy?
Troy was in present-day Anatolia, which
is currently occupied by Turkey. Okay?
The it's it's a place called Hisarlik.
Hisarlik.
Zoom in.
Here we are. Hisarlik. If you zoom out,
you will see it's near the coastline,
but the coastline has shifted. So, all
of Anatolia used to be Greek long before
the Turks even existed.
So, Hisarlik is the site of ancient
Troy.
If you if would you like to if you like
to see
there's a town called Hisarlik, but then
you have uh
Okay, I'm not sure you'll be able to see
much on the satellite images.
But yeah.
So, that's where the Trojan War
happened. The coastline was all the way
inside at the time.
And now it has shifted significantly.
So, the Trojan War is considered by the
Greeks was considered by the ancient
Greeks to have been
the beginning of a of a dark age of
Greece. So, it destroyed the Mycenaean
period of Greek history.
It probably led to immigration into
Italy, which eventually gave rise to
Rome.
And from about 1100 BC to about 800 BC,
there was a dark age in Greece.
And then you have the beginning of of
classical Greek civilization, which is
you know which which culminates with
Alexander the Greek and with it which
ends with the
invasion and the occupation of Greece by
Julius Caesar.
So, the Mycenaeans are the ancestors of
the classical Greeks.
And they
gave rise to the heroes like Agamemnon
and Paris and Menelaus and Hector
Achilles, Ajax and so on. Right? Those
were the Mycenaeans. So, the Mycenaeans
were the ancestors of the classical
Greeks. The classical Greeks were
eventually defeated and occupied by the
Romans, by Julius Caesar and his armies.
And this eventually gave rise to
Byzantium or the Byzantine Empire, which
was the Eastern Roman Empire.
So, even
around the Second World War era, the
people of Greece some people of that
part of of Greece re-
you know, regarded themselves as Romans.
So, that's the entire chronology. It
starts with the Minoans, then you have
the Mycenaeans, then there is a Trojan
War and and dark age, then you have
classical Greece, which ends with the
with the defeat at the hands of the
Romans and the Roman occupation and then
you have the Byzantine Empire,
which lasts for a while, then you have
the Turkic occupation of Byzantium and
Anatolia, which gives rise to the
Ottoman Empire and that brings us to
where we are today. Okay, hopefully you
understand the chronology there.
Okay.
Shubha says, "What was the practice of
witch hunting in Europe? How many women
were burnt alive? The number 35,000 to
60,000 seems under
underestimated, underrated, etc."
Witch burning. It was
um
it was a European custom. It was a
European tradition, which lasted for
several centuries.
Uh what? Between I don't know, 1200 AD
to about between 1100 AD to about 1500
AD or something.
May have ended in the 1400s sometime to
a significant extent. But for several
centuries, there was this nice charming
custom that the Europeans had of uh
burning women alive. Okay?
Now, what is the what was the origin of
this custom and so on? So, Europe, in
case you aren't aware Christianity isn't
native to Europe.
It's it's a foreign imposition on
Europe. Before Christianity existed,
Europe was polytheistic.
Europe was part of the
of the larger Indo-European world.
The gods and goddesses the Europeans
worshipped were offshoots of the old
Vedic gods.
And the European religions or cultures,
whatever you want to call them, were
local manifestations of the of the oral
same culture.
Right? Polytheistic culture with the
same original gods and goddesses, which
then took took different forms and
different shapes and different names in
various parts of Europe.
So, that's what you had in Europe
originally. And in the old polytheistic
European culture, the Indo-European
culture, which we are still familiar
with because we still live it.
So, in that old culture, women had a
good status in so- society. Women had
very prominent roles in society, not as
warriors, unless it was needed, but as
healers, as as as people who uh you
know, passed on wisdom and knowledge and
so on. Right?
So, obviously you had gender roles in
society, which is a horribly malign
thing today. Oh my god, gender roles. Oh
my god, how
how how backward, how how misogynistic
and so on.
You had gender roles throughout history.
And women had they played certain roles.
They played the roles of of healers, of
teachers and so much more.
And so, healing was done by women.
Um and women were highly respected in
society.
In in the Indo-European society. Then
you have the advent of Christianity. You
have the Northern Crusades and various
other things and all and
you know, read Catherine Nixey's The
Darkening Age that book, which will
explain how Christianity was imposed
brutally through brutal force on the on
the native people of Europe.
So,
so Christianity now starts taking root
in Europe, but the old practices, the
polytheistic practices still kind of
linger and people don't want to give up
their the religion of their ancestors.
So, what do you do?
You frighten the hell out of them.
How do you do that? You accuse any woman
who has any old knowledge of being a
witch, of being a devil devil
worshipper.
Any woman who retains old knowledge, who
can who can you know, secretly heal
people, who secretly can pass on the old
knowledge
designate that woman as a witch, as a
Satan worshipper, a devil worshipper, as
someone who communes with the devil,
with Satan.
Right? Accuse her of being a witch and
then burn her alive.
And then that spread like wildfire. So,
the most popular book or second most
popular book in Europe for multiple
centuries was a a Christian book called
the Malleus Maleficarum. Let us Google
this just fantastically charming text.
Okay?
Malleus Maleficarum.
Malleus Maleficarum, The Hammer of the
Witches.
The Hammer of witches of
yeah.
And this was probably either the most
popular book in Europe or the second
most popular book in Europe for several
centuries.
And this book explained how to discover
whether a woman is a witch or not. What
are the tests you can do to to ascertain
the witch-ness or not of a woman? And
what are the means of of
of
killing such women.
So, one of the ways you could discover
whether a woman was a witch or not is
this.
See, let's let's say a woman has been
accused of being a witch. You catch her,
you bring her in front of the of the of
the church men of the priests and all
that.
And they will obviously disrobe her and
make her naked. And then they will test
whether she is a witch or not by
uh tying a heavy you know,
um
tying a heavy rock to her feet
and putting her in a body of water.
So, if she drowns
then there is no effect of Satan on her
and she was not a witch. But if she
floats, then she's a witch and you
should burn her alive. So, if you are
not a witch, you will drown. If you are
a witch, you will float and you will be
burnt alive. So, it is death this way,
death that way. That's one way of
finding out whether a woman is which is
a witch or not. And they had many other
charming ways of finding out of
discovering whether a woman was a witch
or not. So, essentially it was about
exercising control and power over the
people of Europe. It was about
terrorizing the hell out of them.
It was about uh
uh terrorizing
the people so much that they will
abandon their ancestral culture and
religion and become staunch Christians
through fear.
And that was the dark ages of Europe.
Right?
So, um
the old culture respected women.
The new religion that that was brought
in, it was misogynistic. Horribly
misogynistic. And that led to the
practice this this custom, this European
tradition and custom of burning women
alive. And eventually it was it went to
the extent that if you know, if someone
did not like someone, they would accuse
the woman of being a witch and then the
church would be very happy. Okay, one
more soul to burn. Right?
And that that that
that would
make them you know,
enable them to control the people even
more. Even if people were um
falsely accused of being witches, I'm
I'm sure there was no real witch at all
anywhere. Right? Obviously.
And that's how it went. Now,
it was believed for the longest time
that millions of women were burnt as
witches.
But in recent time, you know, very
eminent scholars and academics have done
proper research and they have decided no
millions of women were not burned alive.
It was only a small number, 35 to
40,000, maybe 60,000 at most.
Not even 100,000, not even six figures.
All these old myths, all these old
stories that have been passed on by
through word of mouth, these are myths.
Europe wasn't that barbaric. It was a
modest figure. Only 35 to 60,000 women
were burned alive. Okay?
That's the deal. So they have
whitewashed their history.
They accuse Indians and Hindus of of
being what? Sati, of forcing our widows
to to to burn themselves alive, immolate
themselves alive, which is a complete
colonial fabrication, missionary
fabrication, but they are the ones who
were doing all this.
And now they have whitewashed that down
to to a figure of 35 to 60,000. 60,000
the higher higher limit. Mostly mostly
likely 35,000.
So that's how you whitewash history and
that's how you create historical
narratives. That's how you use history
as a weapon.
Understand this.
All right.
Swapnil Mishra always has interesting
questions. So, the question is what
caused the Aral Sea in Central Asia to
dry up?
And is there any chance it will recover?
Let's go to the map and find out what is
this Aral Sea thing, right?
Um
So I you may have I mean in case you are
a regular viewer of this channel, you
would have heard me speak about Emperor
Kanishka and how his empire stretched
from the Aral Sea to the Caspian Sea all
the way to other parts of the world.
So where is the Aral Sea? There is no
such thing today, but there still is
kind of something
uh which is here.
Shall we zoom in? What's it say?
One second.
Um
Has to be somewhere here. This has to be
the Aral Sea.
This has to be the Aral Sea.
But as Miss Shikha Lake, okay. So let's
put the satellite images on so that we
get some more clarity.
So this
this used to be Okay, let's first Google
Aral Sea, okay? Let's first Google Aral
Sea and you can see the before and after
images of what happened
to this part of the world, okay? So
let's do that. Aral Sea before and
after.
Before and after. Let's go to images.
And look at this.
So you have a before image and after
image. After is disastrous, as you can
see. Look at this.
See what happened here?
Disaster. Look here. Look at the the
satellite images here also as well.
Look at this. 77, 1977, 1989 and 2006.
Uh and there's more and there's more.
It's it's all it's a tale of disaster.
You can see the shrinking over here.
2000 to all the way to 2018.
Now we can go to the satellite images
and uh
Okay, where where are we? So
Uh one second, let me put that on and
then we shall discuss what exactly
happened here.
So
Is No, not this, not this. Okay, so this
is the Aral Sea, okay? By the way,
whatever they say
satellite images
uh
This is the northern portion of the Aral
Sea and there's a dam over here. We
we're going to come back to this dam
because this dam is important.
Uh I forget the name of this dam. It is
Aral something dam.
And this dam has kept the northern
portion of the Aral Sea still kind of
alive. It's kind of revived in the past
few few in the past couple of decades.
But as you can see there's a huge
artificial I mean new desert that has
come up over here, which is where the
Aral Sea used to be. So why did the Aral
Sea go dry? Why did that not happen to
the Caspian Sea is the question. So the
Aral Sea is fed by two rivers, two
iconic rivers, okay? The the modern
names are the Amu Darya
and the Syr Darya.
The historical
name of the Amu Darya was the Vakshu or
the Chakshu River.
Chakshu means eye in Sanskrit, okay?
And another name was the Vakshu River in
Sanskrit. The Syr Darya, its original
Persian name was the Yakhsha
Yakhsha Arta.
Okay, now so let's see where these
rivers are.
Um this has to be
this river here
is the Syr Darya
which is the Yakhsha Arta.
So this is one of the rivers that that
feeds the Aral Sea and it goes all the
way here and it's still kind of feeding
the Aral Sea over here.
As you can see, this is the Syr Darya.
It is draining out into the northern
portion of the Aral Sea, which is still
kind of alive.
And then there is another river
okay?
Um which is called the Amu Darya
which kind of flows in this region
which also used to feed the Aral Sea.
So this is the Amu Darya.
This one here. This river. This is the
Amu Darya. As you can see over here it
says Amu Darya.
So these two rivers used to feed the
Aral Sea. Now this this part of the
world was part of the USSR. Okay, in the
20th century.
And uh the Soviet uh
government or whatever you want to call
it, it decided that it will launch
irrigation schemes in the region.
And they built these big networks of
canals that drained out the waters of
these two rivers, the Amu Darya and the
Syr Darya.
And the canals were not properly
engineered. They did not have proper
embankments and all and so on, which is
why the waters, you know, they they just
spilled out and much of the waters
evaporated and the the water that used
to drain into the Aral Sea, it was all
diverted.
And then there were all these
agricultural projects that were
undertaken in the region and all kinds
of chemicals and fertilizers and whatnot
were was used and this caused the waters
of the Aral Sea to go down down down.
Eventually they became
it became a shallow lake which which you
could walk in, wade in
and it became highly salinated because
because when the water evaporates
there's a lot of salt that's left
behind. And eventually it just dried out
and became a desert. And all the fish
disappeared and obviously it will
disappear. What do you expect, right?
So it's because of this man-made
disaster that the Aral Sea disappeared.
And after 2005 that that dam that I
showed you, that has been put in place
and that has kept
uh the northern the northern part of the
Aral Sea from drying up and it has kind
of revived. And you still you now again
have fish uh fish that have revived over
there and you can do fishing and stuff
over there.
So the northern part of the Aral Sea has
been revived to some extent. Uh it will
be very difficult to revive the southern
part of the Aral Sea because it used to
be such a large large region
and today the the river it's being used
in other ways and hardly anything
reaches that part of you know, the Aral
what used to be the Aral Sea. So I
suppose you could do a 100-year project
or 50-year project in which you could
revive the Aral Sea. I'm sure it's
possible, but it's not going to be easy.
So that's why the Aral Sea disappeared
completely. I mean not completely, but
to a very large extent. The empire of
Emperor Kanishka, it it stretched from
the shores of the Aral Sea to the
Caspian Sea in the northwest
and it had Xinjiang and northern India
and so much more.
So that's the deal with the Aral Sea.
Now
Shub says, how did 12 major
Mahajanapadas come into being and
influence Indian history?
Mahajanapadas.
Can you name the 12 uh Mahajanapadas?
Uh Kashi, Kosala, Anga, Magadha
Vrijji or Vajji, Malla
Kuru Panchala, Avanti, Matsya, etc.
I'm sure I've not named all 12. But uh
you can find you can look at the list.
So you had these 12 Mahajanapadas that
appeared sometime around 1,000 around
1,000 BC.
Somewhere around that time, maybe
slightly before that, maybe a couple of
centuries before that, maybe a couple of
centuries after that.
Most likely after 1,000 BC these 12
Mahajanapadas appeared, okay? Now what's
the deal
with the Mahajanapadas? What's their
history?
So
how did these Maha What the first of
all, what does Janapada mean? The Jana
means people, right? Jana.
Pada means leg or sorry, foot.
So Janapada means
foothold of the people.
Mahajanapada means great foothold of the
people.
Uh and Jana means people as in a group
of people, as in a linguistic group um
a clan, an ethnic group, whatever you
want to call it.
So you had
So as we know, there used to be some
there was a period of our history
which is known as the Saraswati Sindhu
era, right? When our population was
significantly concentrated in the north
and west of India in the Sapta Sindhu
region. Obviously people still lived in
the Ganga plains, Yamuna plains and all
that, but you had this massive urban
gigantic
part of India which was fully urbanized,
fully industrialized and it it straddled
the length and the breadth of the
Saraswati Sindhu region, the Sapta
Sindhu region.
Now there was climate change around 1200
BC and
look India's climate started changing
about 6,000 BC. The Indian rainy season
started declining monotonously
monotonically
around 6,000 BC. Slowly, very gradually,
very imperceptibly, the intensity
of the rainfall decreased over time. And
the volume of rain that we received
decreased over time.
Around 1500 BC, the great river
Saraswati had kind of half dried up.
It no longer reached the western Indian
Ocean, the Sea of Saurashtra. It no no
longer reached it.
It dried out in a big puddle, which
eventually became the Thar Desert, the
desert, the Rajasthan Desert, right?
Um and today it only exists in the north
and it no people call it what? The
Ghaggar-Hakra.
So, the great river dried out.
And around 1200 or 1300 BC,
you had this massive maybe 50-60 years
of climate change, which caused the
bronze bronze age collapse in the
Mediterranean region.
Uh and it also caused a significant
climate change in India as well. So,
people
abandoned They were forced to abandon
the great cities like Mohenjo-Daro,
Harappa, Kalibangan, Rakhigarhi, Lothal,
Dholavira, so on and so forth.
And they had to move to other parts of
the world. So, some Indians went
westwards.
That that process may have begun around
2000 BC because we know that Indians
went westwards and
in and created you know, the
uh Mitanni Empire,
the Hittite Empire, right?
Uh
but Indians also went eastwards and
settled in the great plains of India,
the Ganga plain, the Saraswati the
Yamuna plain and so on.
So, this process was not a sudden
process. It happened over centuries and
the people who lived in the Saraswati
Sindhu region the Sapta Sindhu region,
they migrated to other parts of the
world, mostly eastwards into other parts
of India.
And these groups of people, they would
obviously migrate together.
And they eventually settled in all these
different parts of India, which
eventually became the Mahajanapadas.
Okay?
Um
and so that was the the the origin of
the Mahajanapadas. They So, there is
the So, the climate change happens in
the late late Vedic era.
1500 BC is the late Vedic era and then
you have the end of the period of
antiquity and the beginning of modern
India around 1000 BC.
Which is the period of the Janapadas,
which become the Mahajanapadas and
eventually
stronger Mahajanapadas like Magadh, like
Kosala, like Avanti, like whatever else
they they defeated the weaker ones and
absorbed them.
They absorbed them.
And this process continued, process of
absorption,
annexation.
It eventually led to the unification
of Bharatvarsha
under Magadh,
which set the stage
for the Mauryan Empire.
So, that's a transition from the late
Vedic period to what you could perhaps
call the modern Indian period, which is
about 2 and 1/2 thousand years before
today, 2,500 2,600 years before today.
Uh maybe 3,000 years before today. So,
the transition phase is around 3,000
years before today. From the late Vedic
period to what you could call modern
India and the period of the republics,
the great republics, the Mahajanapadas.
Right?
Uh The Sky Prime says, "Considering how
ancient our Bharati history goes, why do
we consider let's say the the era of the
Mauryan, Shunga or Gupta Empire that
period, why do we consider it to be
ancient?"
That's what I just spoke about, but
yeah, great question. Shouldn't that
period be considered to be a modern or
maybe somewhat recent period to us if we
look at the antiquity of our
civilization? Very good point you make,
sir or ma'am.
So,
yeah, so like I said, the period the the
around 1000 BC, you had a period of
transition
from the late Vedic period to what you
could call a modern period, right? So,
the late Vedic period is the period when
there is climate change and the
Saraswati dries up to a significant
extent and uh
you have people who are forced to
migrate out of the Saraswati Sindhu
region and abandon the great cities of
Mohenjo-Daro, Harappa, Kalibangan,
Rakhigarhi, Lothal, Dholavira and so
many more. Thousands and thousands you
had of cities, towns in this region.
Fully urbanized, fully industrialized.
People had to move out of that because
of climate change.
And many Indians went westwards. At
least some Indians went went westwards
out of India forever. They set up
empires like the Mitanni Empire and the
and the Hittite Empire.
And most Indians are would say would
have gone eastwards into the Ganga
plain, Yamuna plain and other parts of
India, Narmada Narmada plain and settled
in these various parts of India. And
people would have obviously migrated in
groups, not just random migrations. They
would have migrated in groups together
to to keep the society and and
everything else together, unified.
And then they would have migrated to
migrated and settled in various parts of
the Ganga Yamuna plains and Narmada
plains and so on.
And that gave rise to the Mahajanapadas.
Right?
And that eventually gave rise to the
rise of Magadh, which absorbed all the
Mahajanapadas and gave rise to the Nanda
Empire and then the Mauryan Empire.
So, that's So, around 1000 BC, we have a
transition phase from the late Vedic era
to the
very initial Mahajanapada era.
So, that should be called modern Indian
history
or a different phase of Indian history.
And the and the period from 1000 AD
to today should be called the millennium
of humiliation of India because that
part part of period of time, 1000 years,
we were under foreign occupation and we
still are subjugated
mentally at least because we haven't
come out of the British occupation
period of Indian history. We haven't. We
are still very much We are actually
deeper into the period of British
occupation of occupation of India
through the constitution, through the
institutions, through the English
language and so on.
So, yeah, I completely agree with Sky
Prime that you know, it's the the
the year 1000 BC rough is roughly an
inflection point in Indian history where
you are transitioning from the Vedic
late Vedic period to what you could call
a modern period or some or the
Mahajanapada period for sure.
So, it's definitely more recent
considering the antiquity of Bharati
history that goes back at least 6,000 or
8,000 BC
most likely even before that.
Right.
Samarth Pramanik says, "Why did the
Cholas never conquer the whole of the
subcontinent despite having the
strongest army of that time?"
Just like the Mauryan Empire, the Gupta
Empire, the Kushan Empire.
You see, the Mauryan Empire, the Gupta
Empire, the Kushan Empire, the Chola
Empire, they all solved for different
strategic issues.
Okay?
All of these were empires that had very
different characteristics.
Two of these were kind of similar, the
Mauryan Empire and the Gupta Empire.
They both emerged out of Magadh.
They both had their capital at
Pataliputra at least initially.
Right?
So, the Guptas and the Mauryans were
kind of similar in certain senses.
The Kushan Empire,
you could say a significant portion of
its territory
was Central Asia.
At least half was India, northern India
was in India.
But a significant period portion of it
was Central Asia.
A present-day Xinjiang, present-day
Tibet, to the all the way to the shores
of the Aral Sea and the Caspian Sea.
Uh Kanishka fought with various with
what I forget the name of the Persian
king, but he fought.
He fought and he pushed him back and
grabbed some territory.
Right?
So, what was Kanishka doing? What was
the deal with the with the Kushan
Empire?
The Kushan Empire's entire strategy,
grand strategy,
was a strategy of amassing wealth
by by by controlling the the landmass
through which all the trade between
India and Europe happened.
And also to some extent with
with China. The Europeans were majorly
trading with India. This entire myth of
the Silk Road, it's it's a it's a myth.
The major trade between Europe
and
the East was between Europe and India.
Not the not the Chinese. There was
hardly any trade comparative comparable
to India between Europe and China. So,
Kanishka, his strategy was to occupy a
gigantic portion of Central Asia and
control all the trade between India
and Europe and amass tremendous wealth
for the empire as a consequence. And
Kanishka also controlled our western
ports
in Saurashtra, which was also which were
also trading with Rome. So, Kanishka by
doing this was able to control the land
as well as sea routes of trade between
India and the West.
And through that he made India
fabulously rich, fabulously wealthy.
That was Kanishka's grand strategy.
Um
now,
the
Mauryan grand strategy was to control
the entire subcontinent, essentially
during Ashoka's time,
and while the Kushans were these highly
mobile they they had these highly mobile
armed armed forces, mainly equestrian
armed forces based on horses,
uh
the Mauryan strategy was to construct a
network of roads and highways all across
India and control India through that.
And they had direct taxation, direct
control. They did not employ vassals.
The Mauryans, at least Ashok did not
employ any vassals. He controlled the
entirety of the subcontinent
through
a centralized system.
And it was a centrally planned economy
as well.
Right?
Uh
when it comes to the Guptas, it was
similar, but the Guptas used vassalage,
the system of vassalage. So, the
So,
what's his name? Samudragupta conquered
the whole of the subcontinent. He
defeated all the southern most of the
southern southern southern Indian uh
kingdoms.
And he allowed them to continue as
vassals.
He did not defeat the kings and kill
them off. He allowed them to continue on
their thrones, but as vassals who would
serve the Maharajadhiraja.
Okay?
So, that was the deal with the Gupta
Empire. Now, the Cholas were a very
different kind of empire.
Uh
Rajaraja Chola sets the foundation of
the Chola Empire.
And Rajendra Chola takes it to the next
level.
So, the Cholas built India's premier
blue water navy
in the past 2,000 years.
Uh its capabilities were, you could say,
compared to everything else in the in
the world, far better than what India's
navy today is compared to the rest of
the world.
Okay?
And through through that, they were able
to uh
essentially conquer Srivijaya, but not
just conquer Srivijaya Srivijaya,
vassalize the whole of Southeast Asia
all the way to the Philippines.
That's what their strategy was. Their
strategy was to control the maritime
trade. See, without wealth, nothing
works.
So, you need to have a way of
controlling wealth, the flow of wealth,
the flow of goods, the the the the trade
routes.
So, the Chola strategy was to solve for
a different problem. It was to control
the maritime trade routes between India
and Eastern Asia.
And that made the empire fabulously
rich. Now,
Rajendra Chola did conquer did did make
a move on Varanasi.
And he did conquer Varanasi for a bit.
And that's why he came to be known as
the conqueror of the Ganga. And he
created a new capital in in the memory
of the glorious event, Gangaikonda Chola
Cholapuram Gangaikonda Cholapuram,
which today is kind of in ruins, very
sadly.
Uh and at that time, you had the Palas
who were ruling in that area. And he
defeated the Palas,
which were which was a Bengali empire um
kingdom, wasn't it?
But for the Cholas to go and conquer
northern India
would take a tremendous amount of
resources. They would need horses. They
would need a whole different set of
strategies and tactics.
And they would have to fight their own
people.
And you had very powerful kingdoms up
north.
You had the Paramaras, you had the
Chahamanas or the Chauhans.
You had the Palas. And you already had
the unfortunate introduction of the of
the Turkic invasions into India. The
Cholas
probably did not want to deal with all
of that at this point in time. So, they
decided that let's stick to our
strengths. Let us play to our strengths.
We are a We have the probably the
world's premier blue water navy.
Let's use that to our advantage and
create a maritime empire.
So, that's the deal. All of these
empires that you're mentioning, they
solved different strategic problems.
And the objective of any empire is to
control the flow
of trade, the flow of wealth, and to
amass as much wealth as possible, which
is what allows the empire to run
function properly. And it it's what
keeps the people happy. If If you have
If you are amassing wealth, if you are
gaining wealth all the time, then you
are able to give your people prosperity
and high
quality of life, which is what any
emperor needs, no matter how powerful he
is. You don't want to deal with an
unhappy population. You You never want
to do that. So, that was the deal.
But very interesting question. Why did
all these different empires have
different
different strategies and different
policies and, you know, different
outlooks?
Manu Wadi Lab
says, "Why do Indian orthodox parents
consider love marriage to be a taboo
and against our culture
when Lord Krishna's marriage to
Maharukmini, Masatyabhama, Arjun's
marriage to Subhadra, Lord Shiva's
marriage to Ma Parvati, these were all
love marriages?"
Interesting question.
So,
look, in uh
in sociology or whatever you want to
call it, there is the concept of
hypergamy,
hypogamy, and homogamy.
Hypergamy means you're marrying upstream
or you're marrying up.
See, in any civilization,
in any advanced society,
you have a stratification of society.
Society is stratified in a hierarchical
set of classes or castes or whatever you
want to call it. In India, they call it
caste to demonize Hinduism.
But anywhere in the world, any properly
functioning society
has hierarchical classes in society. You
have the elites, then you have the
merchants, then you have the warriors,
then you have this, that, etc. etc. etc.
That's the way a functioning society is
organized. That's how the way a
functioning army or military is
organized. That's the way a functioning
whatever else is organized. A
corporation is also organized like this.
Any functioning group of people needs to
have a hierarchy.
And with
hierarchy comes status.
It With hierarchy comes power.
With hierarchy comes wealth. So, people
on people who are who belong to a higher
stratum of society,
they will generally either have more
power or more wealth or more status.
Typically, all three. Sometimes not all
three, but at least something will be
higher.
Right?
So, in India, we have the so-called
caste called Brahmins.
They typically were not powerful. They
did not have
access to the means
uh to the to the means of violence,
which is weapons and soldiers.
But they had higher status because they
were they were the the the preservers
and transmitters of knowledge. So, they
were considered even higher in status
than the warriors who were actually the
most powerful. And that's how it was.
Now,
now that we understand this, so we have
in any society
different classes of people. And you
have it in today in India also. Today,
they say that we have to annihilate
caste, blah blah blah. Good, fantastic,
annihilate caste. But then why do you
have high what middle middle class and
lower class and upper class and
creamy layer and all that nonsense?
You're creating new classes.
You're creating the same old nonsense
all over again. Right?
But that's the way it is. Society is
always stratified. Any functioning
society is stratified. And a highly
civilized society has even more
stratification.
Now,
now that we understand this,
why is love marriage taboo? It's not
taboo.
It's
your parents won't object to you
if you fall in love with a boy or a
girl, depending on your gender, because
there are two genders, depend
depending on your gender,
um
they will not object to you falling in
love
and wanting to marry somebody of equal
status,
the same
stratum of society,
or maybe
perhaps a higher stratum of society.
Right?
So, let's say you come from a family
that earns, let's say,
cumulatively 10 lakhs a month, which is
probably what would be considered to be
middle class.
And uh
if you fall in love with somebody who's
who comes from a family that earns 1
lakh a month, your parents will be
deeply upset.
But if you fall in love with someone and
you want to marry someone who comes from
a similar background, 10 12 lakhs a
month, 15 lakhs, 20 lakhs, they'll say,
"Good good, beta." Or "Good, beti."
And if you fall in love with somebody
who's earning 10 crores a month, they'll
say, "Be careful. You may get into
trouble because, you know,
there's a difference in class."
That's how it goes.
Okay?
That's how it goes in all societies.
That's how it has historically always
gone.
So, it's not a taboo. It's not against
our culture.
When Lord Krishna married very various
ladies, he would have probably married
ladies See, he was a very high status
person, Lord Krishna.
He was
one of the world's greatest statesman.
He was a great warrior. He was a king.
For him, it was okay to marry anybody.
Anybody.
Ideally, somebody who's at the level of
a king or a queen or a princess or
something, but
as a king, he could do whatever he want
wanted. And that's how it went for him.
And Arjun and so on. So, I I hope that
explains why, you know, parents
typically consider love marriage to be
taboo. Because, see, when you're
children, you don't understand class and
status and all these things, then you
typically, you know, love is blind. You
may fall in love with someone who is
the the son or a daughter of a
billionaire or somebody who
is the son or a daughter of a pauper.
Okay, I have nothing against any class
society. When I use the word pauper, I'm
just using it in an illustrative sense,
not in a pejorative sense, please.
Somebody will start commenting now
otherwise.
So, that is the reason why you have
these issues.
Because children, when you are young,
when you're 18, 19, 20, even 25, until
you reach a certain age, you don't
understand these things.
And you then, you know,
may get into situations which would be
socially socially awkward for your
parents and
so on. So, that's the reason.
Feels strong man says, "In terms of
early city building, why were the
Americans hell-bent on constructing new
cities like Chicago or other cities in
the West Coast specifically in the grid
layout?
Did they draw inspiration from cities
like Paris? Why do our Indian cities
that existed for 2000 that existed for
2000 years still not have a grid layout
despite being
better, in my opinion?
Why did the Americans build their cities
along a grid layout?
Because it makes sense.
It leads to better city planning, town
planning.
You know, it's easy to reach any part of
the city just using a grid grid system.
It just makes sense. It's it's a
superior way of planning a city.
That's why they constructed the cities
when they See, what the Americans did is
that they conquered an entire continent
of swept aside the natives, wiped them
out, genocided them. And this entire new
land that they had, they could create
any city they wanted in any way they
wanted. So, they went about creating
cities in the best way possible because
they had this land that the gods had
given them or their god had given them.
And they could start from a blank slate.
They did not have the legacy of cities
that were like 2000 years old. And then,
what do we do with this? It's already
constructed in in a certain way. No,
they could build from scratch. That's
why they started with the best possible
system, which is the grid system.
Right?
I'm not sure if they were inspired by
cities from cities like Paris or
whatever. See, Paris, was it constructed
from on a grid system? It was not.
If you go back a thousand years, Paris
was a town, a little small town with a
fortress on the banks of the Seine. Then
it just emerged organically from there.
Today it is slightly more organized,
definitely. London also, if you look at
old London before the great fire of
whatever year it was, it was a disaster
of a city, horribly unplanned. But then
a miraculous fire happened in London,
and then they were able to rebuild the
city from scratch.
Huh?
So, the Americans, they built the cities
using the grid system because it just
made sense. Now, the question is about
India.
Why do our Indian cities that have
existed for 2000 years not have a grid
layout? Let's go to the map, yes?
Let's go to the map.
I agree with you that if you look at
various modern Indian cities, which I
will not go to otherwise it will create
controversies, they are horribly
unplanned. So, I will not talk about any
modern Indian city. Now, let's Google
something. Hm?
Let's Google Dholavira.
Dholavira is over here. Look, zoom out.
It's in the eye of Gujarat.
Over here.
Let's zoom in. Zoom in. Zoom in.
Zoom in.
Let's see the satellite image.
Dholavira.
Harappan era, you know,
archaeological site. So, this is not
that. This is some alleged museum here.
Look at this. This is a museum,
apparently.
These are the Indian standards of today.
But look at the Indian standards of old
times.
There's a very little amount of the city
that's still visible.
But if you look at the layout, it's a
god damned grid layout.
Hm?
This city is how old? 5000 plus years
old? Yes?
If you go to Lothal, if you go to
Harappa, if you go to Mohenjo-Daro, if
you go to Rakhigarhi, if you go to
Kalibangan, if you go to all these
ancient cities which are more than 5000
years old, they are all laid out in a
grid structure.
Yes? And then, there's something more
interesting.
In the Gulf of Khambat, okay, this place
is called the Gulf of Khambat. There's
this town called Khambat, which used to
be a great port in the past. Now, this
entire Gulf is silted, so the port is
unusable.
But in the Gulf of Khambat, there there
is this cluster of sunken cities that
are more than 10,000 years old.
And if you see the sonar images,
okay? I'm not sure they're even
available now on the internet, but if
you look at the way those cities are
laid out, they are laid out in a grid
grid structure, more than 10,000 years
old. If you look if you go to Dwarka,
it is
so the old city of Dwarka is sunken
along the coast somewhere, and that's
why they had to rebuild a new city.
And that old city of Dwarka, which is
underwater,
which is at least 8000 years old, that
is also laid out in a grid structure.
But if you look at modern Indian cities,
they are laid out in a completely
haphazard structure because those are
the post-1947 standards of India.
Abysmally low standards of India. That's
the standards your politicians and
leaders have and your town planners and
bureaucrats have.
Okay? So, that's how our standards have
declined.
Ayush Singh says, "What is this term
Sinosphere? What does it mean?
Why are Japan and South and Korea
considered to be part of the Sinosphere?
Uh because
um these
these cultures, these these
countries, let's say,
they received Buddhism
from China, which is an Indian culture,
which is an Indian export. Uh apart from
influencing the language of East Asia,
to what extent was China influential?
And please draw a comparison between
that and the influence that India has,
okay?
Sinosphere. The Sinosphere, just like
Indosphere, means
uh the the region that has been
the geographical the geographic region
that has historically been influenced
strongly by China. That's the
Sinosphere. So, which are the regions
that are part of the Sinosphere? Vietnam
is there.
Um
uh Korea
and Japan.
Is part of the of the Sinosphere.
And what else do we have? Uh today you
could say Singapore to some extent is
part of the Sinosphere because there are
so many Chinese who kind of dominate
Singapore.
And also Mongolia because half of
Mongolia is under Chinese occupation and
so on.
So, that's the Sinosphere. Now,
the question is why are Japan and Korea
considered to be part of the Sinosphere?
Japan received Buddhism, an Indian
culture, from China. But that's Indian
culture. That's not Chinese. And the
same goes for
Korea itself.
So,
why are Japan and Korea part of the
Sinosphere? Considered to be part of the
Sinosphere?
See,
the Chinese script
of writing,
it was transmitted to Japan and Korea.
And the Japanese, if you look at the
Japanese script, it is derived from the
Chinese script.
If you look at the Korean script of
writing,
let's let's Google it, right? Quickly.
We'll we'll take a look at that.
Okay. So,
first let's see the Chinese script.
Chinese script.
So, this is what the Chinese script
looks like. Okay? This is Chinese
writing.
We are we are all familiar with what it
looks like. Now, let's look at the
Japanese script.
Japanese script. So, once again, as you
can see,
it's very similar
to the Chinese script. Look I mean, we
don't know how to read this, but you can
see how similar it is. Let's look at the
Korean script.
Hangul.
So, once again, as you can see, it is
very strongly influenced by the Chinese
script.
So, there you have clear influence from
China, unquestionably
clear influence.
Then if you look at um
the the then there is the fact that
China did not merely export only
Buddhism and Indian culture to China and
Japan and Korea, they also exported
Confucianism and Taoism
to Japan and Korea. The Chinese had this
imperial system that
strongly influenced the Japanese
imperial system and the Korean
administrative and and uh
you know,
kingly system. Korea was never an
empire, it's too small, but they had
kingdoms which were influenced by
Chinese by the Chinese imperial system.
The Chinese have this administrative
system, the Chinese ancient version of
the IAS, let's say, okay? Far superior.
Uh which strongly affected uh
which strongly
influenced
the way the Japanese imperial
bureaucracy was and the way the the
Korean
uh kingdoms' bureaucracy and
administrative administrative structure
was like.
So, there once again you have this.
The fact that the Chinese eat with
chopsticks, I think it's Chinese export.
We I think I think we all understand
that. The Japanese use that, the Koreans
use that, the Vietnamese use that. The
Vietnamese history has also been
similarly influenced by China.
Uh so, a lot of what China has exported
has been Indian culture into Japan, into
Korea, into Vietnam, etc.
But the Chinese claim that Buddhism is
is now a Chinese religion. It's been in
China for 2000 years. And the Chinese
have adopted it in uh and and and
adapted it to the Chinese way of life
and so on. So, it's now a Chinese
religion. That's what they say.
Well, okay, we can agree or disagree,
that's that's a different story, but
these are the ways in which China has
influenced
uh
Japan Japan Korea and Vietnam. So it's
not just the Indian export, but the
entire Chinese way of life and stuff
that has
that has influenced these parts of the
world and that's why they are part of
the Sinosphere. Now even Mongolia is
being influenced by that to some extent.
Tibet is now anyway it's been annexed by
China.
So the Chinese language and whatever
else will be
imposed on the Tibetans and so on.
A comparison with what the influence in
India has.
The influence that India has on Japan on
Korea
Mongolia it's indirect influence.
Whatever Indian culture which is immense
amount of Indian culture which were
absorbed by Japan and Korea, they were
all they all came through China. So
there's a strong Chinese flavor also to
it. For example
there is the concept of Dhyana.
Dhyana meditation Dhyana practices and
all that.
The Chinese called it Chan.
Okay, their pronunciation of Dhyana was
Chan and that when when it went to Japan
the Japanese further changed it to Zen.
So they have something called Zen
Buddhism which is nothing but Dhyana,
right?
So so you can see that there is clear
unmistakable Indian influence in Japan
and Korea. In Korea also similar things.
If you look at the the deities that the
Japanese worship, the Buddhist deities
most of these are Indian Hindu deities
actually.
Beyond the Buddha himself you have all
the other Hindu deities like Saraswati
like
Ganapati
like Shiva like Kubera and so on. All
these Indian gods and demigods like
Yakshas like Kubera, these are all part
of the deities that the Japanese worship
which are not Buddhist deities but Hindu
deities. In Buddhism you're supposed to
worship the Buddha. You're not even
supposed to worship the Buddha actually,
but you know that's how things have
changed.
And the Japanese called
Saraswati Benzaiten. They called
they call
Ganesh Kangiten and so on.
So the Indian influence is secondary
influence. It's it's indirect influence,
but even then it's very strong
influence.
Nirvana Shanks says, "Why did the
Western Roman Empire fall in the 5th
century AD despite maintaining advanced
technology infrastructure and a large
military for centuries, whereas the
Eastern Roman Empire or the Byzantine
Empire survived for nearly a millennium
more under similar pressures?"
So the the Western Roman Empire had
advanced technology infrastructure and a
large military for centuries and yet it
crumbled.
Well, India had advanced technology
infrastructure and a large military and
yet we fell to the Turkic invasions.
What was the reason? We were fragmented
and we had poor leadership. Even if we
had good leaders they were not
powerful enough because the country was
fragmented. Similarly, when it comes to
the Roman Empire we had similar
situations, right?
So what are the factors that caused the
collapse eventual collapse of the
Western Empire? First of all political
instability. That's one of the key
things you need to have. Political
stability is is key to the survival of
an empire. So the Western Roman Empire
it faced frequent leadership changes.
Frequent rapid revolving door leadership
changes. One emperor comes and another
one goes. This is assassination or war
or thrown and another one comes in and
so on, right?
So you had this severe political
instability and what this caused what
what was the effect of this political
instability? The effect was that the
real power it moved from the emperors to
military commanders.
And this led to a fragmentation of the
authority in Rome.
So there is no clear authority. There is
hidden authority like the dictators of
Pakistan, the military dictators of
Pakistan and the emperor becomes like
the prime minister of Pakistan.
That sort of thing.
Because of this you have all kinds of
other
problems that that creep into the
administration into society. There is
corruption. There is economic decay.
You know, there is less attention paid
to the things that keep society running
in a good way. Right? There is loss of
revenue.
Um
Different commanders fight each other in
the armed forces. There is overextension
of the armed forces. It's very difficult
to fund large large armed forces. It's
hard to maintain infrastructure. Even if
you have infrastructure you can't you
know do the upkeep of the
infrastructure. Then because of all
these things you have various provinces
that fall to barbarian invasions. The
Ostrogoths and the Visigoths and the
Huns and whatnot, right? The Vandals
and so on. Yeah, so these so-called
barbarians they repeatedly breached the
borders of Rome and the Roman you know
the territory it slowly starts declining
as it starts contracting.
Um
Another issue was that the Roman
military eventually became over-reliant
on mercenaries.
What kind of mercenaries? Non-Roman
mercenaries. Barbarian mercenaries.
Visigoths Ostrogoths Ostrogoths Vandals
and Huns and whatnot.
And if you are reliant on these foreign
mercenaries you have to eventually
settle them in Rome and give them Roman
territory.
Who will that make unhappy? The Romans.
Have you seen this somewhere before?
So all these things they weakened Rome.
They weakened Rome. They made the people
more and more unhappy. This this illegal
immigration, right? Because of this
cities like Rome became overcrowded,
unhappy, unhealthy. The food production
decli-
decreased because the barbarians did not
know how to do agriculture, but they'd
taken agricultural lands.
Um so there is low food production. The
technology disintegrates. There is
constant infighting, constant warfare.
Trade is disrupted. Hm? So these are the
reasons why Rome collapsed eventually.
Decline of standards. Decline of you
know because they stopped caring about
basic things.
Why did the Eastern Empire the the the
Byzantine Empire survive far longer?
So first of all it was in a great
location, okay? Very highly defensible
location. The city Constantinople had
massive walls and they had a massive
military. They had water on three sides.
Um
That's just the city Constantinople, but
they had a far better administration.
They had a far more stable
administration. They had a far more
centralized administration. They
maintained economic discipline, economic
strength. They adapted better than the
Western Roman Empire
to shifting alliances to different
geopolitical threats. They adapted
diplomatically. They adapted
economically. They adapted militarily,
right?
Um and they also had the advantage of
geography.
And obviously when the Byzantine Empire
eventually fell they it fell from a
from a direction that they had not
expected which is a land-based invasion
from Central Asia.
The barbaric Turks, right?
So
these are the differences between the
Eastern and the Western Roman Roman
Empires and that explains why the
Western Roman Empire disintegrated
mainly because of all these policies
that were bad for the empire because of
declining standards and so on. And the
East survived longer because of the
reasons I just
stated.
Shub says, "What was the society like
during the Vedic age in India?" It was
very different from anything you have
today.
The society of our ancestors was very
different from anything we have today
during the Vedic age. Now where is
What is this Vedic age? When did it
happen is the first question we need to
ask ourselves.
If you read your textbooks
most Indian textbooks. These days I hear
that some textbooks have been changed a
little bit. Maybe CBSE, maybe something
else.
Some changes have happened which is
good. Thank you.
But most textbooks in India still
will tell you that the Vedic age was
between 1500 BC to 1000 BC.
After the Aryan no migration not
invasion now. It's migration. That's
that's nonsense. There was no Aryan
invasion. There was no migration.
The Aryans are us. We are the original
Aryans. Us Indians, okay? Aryans were
not some fictitious white race of people
race of white people.
Um
So
So the Vedic age age was not after 1500
BC.
The Vedic age
is
closer to 6000 BC.
And I have explained this so many times
I will not explain it today.
Uh so the Vedic age was closer to 6000
BC
than to 1500 BC.
And it was a completely pastoral era. A
pastoral period of Indian history. What
does this fantastic word pastoral mean?
It means rural.
India was a rural society at the time.
India was a clan-based society. The
population density was incredibly low.
Compared to not just today, compared to
the Saraswati Sindhu phase of Indian
history.
During the Saraswati Sindhu phase of our
history
our population in the Saraswati Sindhu
region, the Sapta Sindhu region was
probably around 5 million individuals.
Which was the world's largest density of
people anywhere in the world
at that time.
Today it's 1.4 billion people which is a
whole different story. But during the
Vedic age it would be have been a
fraction of the population during the
Saraswati Sindhu period of our history.
So we had clan
a clan-based society.
And you had different clans who lived in
different parts of India
of northern and western India.
Some lived in the Ganga Yamuna plains.
Some lived in the Saraswati Sindhu
plains Saraswati Sindhu valleys
and so on. The society was completely
rural.
You had forts, fortresses which were
like
not like huge fortresses, small
fortresses,
more like the ring forts or whatever you
would find in Europe or whatever, Uland
etc.
Sandbyborg
So, that's the kind of society you had.
And uh
the currency, the major source of wealth
was cows, cattle.
The more cattle you had, the wealthier
you were. Which explains why we did not
eat cattle. You don't eat your currency
notes, right?
And because and that's why we also
considered cattle to be, you know,
uh whatever we consider them to be.
So, the subcontinent was full of forests
at that time. Today it is largely
deforested. It was full of forests and
it was very mysterious
at the time.
And uh the lifestyle was, like I said,
pastoral.
And it was a meat-eating lifestyle,
which will make some people very
unhappy. No, no, sir. No, Vedas are
non-violent. What non-violence Vedas?
Have you read the Rigveda?
We were a warrior class of warrior
society. And we were meat-eaters.
And that's why we were winners. Today
we've become a bunch of
softies.
Carb-maxing softies, right?
So, uh that's what the society was like.
It was a warrior society. Obviously you
had
agriculture.
You had
other classes in society, obviously.
Uh but
and and and the gods that were
worshipped at the time were also very
different. The greatest of gods
was
Indra.
And at that time you did not use the
word Shiva. You used the word Rudra.
Om Namo Bhagavate Rudraya.
Right? So, in the Rigveda, the I don't
think there's any mention of the word
Shiva. It's always Rudra who's mentioned
in the Rigveda.
And Rudra obviously Shiva. Eventually
the name changes, right?
Uh yeah, so that's kind of what society
was like during the Vedic Age. Our
ancestors were meat-eaters. I I know it
will make some people very unhappy.
Because we want to back-project our
today's lifestyle onto our ancestors,
which doesn't make any sense. We're
talking about a period that is like
8,000 years ago, maybe even older than
that.
It was a different world at the time.
Your ancestors were different than what
you are.
You people have changed. Today our
standards have declined decreased
dramatically.
Okay. Amisha says, "Why did Roman
emperors mostly adopt while European
monarchs were obsessed with bloodlines?"
Outstanding question.
It's very interesting.
Roman emperors typically adopted
um
individuals who they who they designated
as the next emperor.
But typically, even if you look at
India, there was no there was very
little adoption at all. It was all based
on bloodlines. So, if I am the emperor,
my son, one of my sons,
typically the firstborn son,
will become the next emperor. Otherwise,
one of my more capable sons who I have
designated that you're going to be the
emperor, will become the next emperor.
That's how it was.
Uh generally it was based on
primogeniture.
Firstborn becomes the firstborn son
becomes the next king or emperor. That's
how it was. But the Romans, they had
this
um
practice of adoption. So, why was this?
It was pragmatic. It made sense.
Um Roman society was merit-based
society.
It It didn't mean that other societies
were not merit-based, but the Romans
were very pragmatic. They understood
that succession is very important. If we
mess up succession, everything is over.
So, we have to ensure that, you know, my
family, my son, I'll make sure that they
are rich and they're taken care of, but
as far as the administration of the
empire is concerned, I will ensure that
the right person becomes the next
emperor.
So, Roman emperors would typically
designate who the next emperor would be
and they would adopt that person to
become their their successor.
There was this period of time called the
Five Good Emperors or something. Let's
Let's Google that.
The Five Good Emperors. The five
five good five or no?
Five good emperors
of Rome.
Yes, Nerva, Trajan Hadrian, Antonius
Antoninus Pius, and Marcus Aurelius. The
Five Good Emperors, Britannica.
Right?
So, you had these five emperors and
um you have successively adopted heirs
only distantly related to the
predecessor if at all.
And then you have the Antonine emperors
and so on.
So, the Romans had this practice. It was
a good practice. It ensured that the
right emperor comes to power because
see, like I've spoken about many times
in this show,
what makes or breaks an empire
is the succession.
Kingdom, empire, whatever, succession is
the most important thing, the most
critical thing. For example, when I
discuss geopolitics, people ask me about
Vladimir Putin. I say that Putin will be
considered to be Putin the Great by
history if he gets his succession right.
If he gets the succession wrong when he
moves on from power and the next person
who will be in charge of Russia will be
a weak person who will mess up
everything mess everything up, then
everything that Putin has worked so hard
for will be washed down the toilet.
Essentially.
Right? Succession is the most important
thing. You have so many examples in
history where botched successions
destroyed kingdoms, destroyed empires,
and led to disastrous
periods of centuries of misery.
Sometimes the entire annihilation of an
empire or a culture entirely.
Botched succession.
So, if you want to ensure the right
person will succeed you, then the
most practical, the most pragmatic way
of doing it is by appointing a successor
who is adopted by you. So, that's why
the Romans did that. It made a lot of
sense.
The Baron Zemo says, "Was the conversion
of Andean cultures to Christianity
a process of spiritual erasure
similar to what happened in India under
colonialism?"
We're talking about the Inca Empire in
the Andes in South America.
So, first of all, let's take a look at
the geography before we discuss the
matter.
We're talking about the 1500s. The 1500s
AD.
And we're talking about
South America here, the Andean cultures,
which is western Sorry. Yeah, western
Peru.
Uh where is Yeah, somewhere here. Which
Is this Machu Pic- This is Titicaca,
yes.
So, you had the Inca Empire in this
region, which was destroyed by the
Spaniards.
Um
And what the Spaniards did is that they
very rapidly imposed Christianity by
brutal force on the natives.
On the Inca people of the region. And
today a lot of the people who live in
this region, even if they are of native
uh heritage, native blood, most of them
still Today they would practice
Christianity. There are some elements of
the original culture that still kind of
survive, at least in in Peru,
but most people have been forcibly
converted to Christianity through brutal
force. That's what the Spaniards
did.
So, is this similar?
Is this process of spiritual
erasure similar to what happened in
India under colonialism?
Look, let's not use the word
colonialism. Let's Let's use the proper
word, which is for the proper term,
which is foreign occupation. You had two
periods of foreign occupation of India.
One is the Turkic occupation of India.
And the second is the
the European occupation of India or the
British occupation of India.
During the Turkic occupation of India,
there was
the sustained effort to destroy India's
culture,
to eradicate India's religion, and to
impose by force a foreign religion on
India, which was Islam. Right?
Um and it succeeded to a small extent.
Surprisingly, it did not really succeed.
Um because even in 1947, just before the
partition of India, when you still had a
unified India under British occupation,
you still had majority Hindu population
in India.
So, even after 1,000 years of
occupation,
after the
beginning of the occupation, India did
not convert. So, it did not work.
They tried their best.
At least the Turks they did. Afghanistan
Gandhara, it almost entirely got
converted. Uh in the late 1980s and
1990s, you still had maybe 100,000
non-Muslims in Afghanistan, Hindus and
and Sikhs, right?
And those are not Indians, they were
Afghans. Like today we are Indians and
we are not Afghans, right? But those
were actual Afghans and who were the
descendants of the original population
that had resisted conversion.
So, what the Turks attempted in India
was similar to what the Spaniards did
in
what is now Peru.
And also in Mexico, Tenochtitlan. But it
failed to a large extent in India.
India was super resilient. Then the
British came in India.
They also sought to do that.
But they did not employ force. They were
far more insidious. They changed the
education system. They imposed the
foreign education system on India and
they made it such that
unless you get educated through the
through their education system, you will
not get a job in India. So, it became a
matter of survival to be educated
through the Indian
through the English education system and
that system still persists today.
After 1947, everything has been made
worse.
So, because of successive decades and
and generations of deradication of of
deracination,
today India is possibly far more
amenable
to getting converted to foreign
religions than it was
even 40 years ago, even 50 years ago.
Forget about 1947.
Compared to 1980,
Indians are far more likely to convert
to a foreign religion today.
And that process is is continuing.
So, successive Indian governments have
continued the same policies of of
of deracinating Indians through the
education system and so on.
So, that process of cultural and
spiritual erasure that the Spaniards
attempted in
in
the
what is now Peru, the Inca Empire,
that similar something similar to that
was tried by the Turks in India,
succeeded to a small extent which
eventually led to the partition of India
because of
British policies and agendas. But today,
Indians are more likely to convert and
and I think today you have industrial
scale conversions that are right now
being conducted in India by foreign
forces and the Indian government is
completely
either oblivious to it or it is allowing
this to happen for whatever reason.
Amisha says, why how and why did humans
start walking upright? What came first,
large brains or bipedalism?
So, we will assume for this discussion
that humans, Homo sapiens, originated in
Africa.
There if there is new evidence that
turns up eventually that maybe we
originated somewhere else, we will
change our opinion, okay? We should
always be willing to adapt your
worldview to new emerging information
which is
like legitimate information. Right now,
we're going to assume that humans
originated in Africa, Homo sapiens,
Jebel Irhoud, North Africa, 400,000
years before today, let's say.
Now, bipedalism comes way before Homo
sapiens.
I believe Australopithecus,
one of the ancient hominin species,
from about 4 million years before today,
Australopithecus was the first probably
to start walking in a bipedal manner, a
bipedal gait.
So, why did our distant ancestors from 4
5 6 7 million years before today, why
did they start becoming bipedal? Why?
They earlier used to crawl on all all
fours like any typical mammal, like a
dog, like a cat, like an elephant, like
a giraffe or whatever.
All are quadrupedal mammals, right?
But so, why did our ancestors start
walking on two feet or attempting to do
that? See, today if you look at
bears,
you will see that bears are kind of
capable of walking on two on two feet if
they have to. They can stand up and look
around. They can even walk on two feet,
but they prefer to walk on four feet.
So, so bears have that kind of
adaptation.
Dogs don't have it. Even the dog even
the dogs and bears are very closely
related. You can see their faces very
similar, right? And bears, have you
heard them
have you heard them vocalize? They bark
like dogs, bears, but a pretty booming
bark, woof woof.
Similarly, cats.
Cats are also capable of standing up on
two feet if they have to, but they
prefer to be on four feet.
So, why did this adaptation adaptation
happen in humans? It's because the
terrain
of Africa changed. Not the terrain, but
the the vegetation, the the flora of
Africa changed. Where what used to be
dense forests
gradually gave way to grasslands and
savanna.
And when you no longer have this thick
canopy of trees all the way god knows
how many meters, when you just have
grasslands which are like a couple of
feet tall, then it makes sense to go up
on two feet and look around, peer around
and get gather more intelligence of
about what's happening around you.
And probably that is what led to this
eventual adaptation adaptation that
humans became kind of quasi bipedal.
And we already had these digits, right?
These opposing digits, the thumb which
is an opposing digit which gave us this
superb advantage that we could
hold things in our hand, manipulate
objects.
So, when we started becoming bipedal,
we also became capable of carrying
things in our hands, tools for example,
which gave us a tremendous
right? So, I think that is what led to
us becoming gradually over hundreds of
thousands of years, millions of years,
bipedal in nature.
But if you look at the skull
volume, the cranial volume of
Australopithecus,
it is very similar to today's
chimpanzees and gorillas.
First of all, let's see what
Australopithecus would have looked like,
okay?
Australopithecus
Australopithecus.
So, yeah, this
fine ancestor of ours, possibly ancestor
or definitely
relative of ours, that's what they
looked like and their cranial capacity
was similar to chimpanzees and gorillas
of today.
Then you have Homo erectus.
Homo erectus which is more human-like,
but still not modern human and even the
the cranial capacity of Homo erectus was
about the somewhat better than
Australopithecus Australopithecus, but
nothing similar nothing comparable to
our cranial capability.
And eventually you
you have
So, you have Homo habilis, Homo erectus
and eventually Homo sapiens. So, what
I'm trying to say is that
the bipedal gait came first. The the
the ability to walk on two feet came
first and the expansion of the brain and
cranial capacity came later
because when you start walking on two
feet, suddenly you can see so much more
and your brain has to process so much
more information. So, it makes sense to
selectively adapt,
you know, through natural selection for
larger and larger brain capacity which
is larger yeah, larger and larger skull
capacity.
So, so bipedalism came first several
million years before larger brain sizes.
The larger brain sizes were an
adaptation which were forced upon us by
the fact that we had become bipedal and
we were having to process so much more
information and data in real time. So,
it made sense to sense to have larger
brains to be able to do that in real
time.
Rishi says, how far east did the Sakas
or the Scythians travel? Because of the
Scythian style art of the upper
Xiajiadian
culture Xiajiadian culture
suggests that they traveled as far east
as the coast of the Pacific Ocean in
eastern China. Okay.
The Xiajiadian culture, it is
located
north
west of of Korea, present-day Korea.
Let's let's Google this Xiajiadian
culture.
And they have artwork that is very
swastika-like at times. So,
Xiajiadian
Xiajiadian culture.
Culture, all right, Xiajiadian.
Upper Xiajiadian culture. If you look at
the images, you will see that it's north
west of present-day Korea.
And as you can see, it's far far in the
east of China, right? Present-day China.
Scythia was Central Asia.
So, as you can see, that's it's far away
from what is traditionally called
Scythia. But if you look at their art,
you can see the swastika-like shapes.
And if you look at other things, it's
it's very similar to the kind of
artifacts and culture that the Scythians
had,
the Sakas.
And the Sakas were an ancient
Indo-Iranian people in in ancient Indic
people who probably were descendants of
some of the Indians who had been exiled
after the Battle of the Ten Kings and
who settled in Central Asia for for a
few millennia before reentering India
about 2,300 or so years ago.
So, Indians who left and then returned
to India.
And the Scythians were nomads, horse
riders, slave traders. Oh, yes,
Scythians were slave traders for sure.
And they had absorbed cultures which
were not ours. So, they were more
relaxed with the
with the cultural taboos like slavery
which we did not practice. And they had
the Scythians had also intermixed,
interbred with various other peoples
like the like the Indic peoples, like
the more Europoid peoples and so on. So,
the Scythians kind of looked different
different from standard issue Indians
and Persians.
And the Scythians,
how far east did they travel? Look, if
you look at the Kushans,
you could perhaps make an argument that
the Kushans are the easternmost
Scythians.
But the Kushans had some characteristics
that were different from the Scythians
like they were not that nomadic.
And yeah.
Now, the question is we saw where the
Shajadian culture was located northwest
of Korea
and their culture is very similar to
their cultural artifacts that are found
in the archaeological record are pretty
similar
to Scythian artifacts. At least they
look like they're influenced by Scythian
artifacts. So, does it mean that the
Scythians had traveled all the way east
to the northwest of Korea?
I would say that maybe the truth is
somewhere in between.
If the Scythians were present in
the Tarim Basin region
and if you could consider the the
Tokharians the Tushara people or the or
the origin the ancestors of the Kushans
to be the easternmost Scythians, then
it's possible that the Shajadian people
would have had contact with the Tushara
people who were Scyth- kind of like
Scythians. And maybe that contact, the
cultural exchange and whatnot, it would
have possibly led to
the kind of Scythian-style art etc. that
you find in the uh arti- uh in the
archaeological artifacts left behind by
the upper Shajadian people. So, I think
it's a combination of two things. I
don't think the Scythians themselves
went all the way far
uh to the northwest of Korea. Maybe it
was because of the
contact, cultural and other contacts
between the Tusharas the Tokharians or
or Kushans
and the Shajadian people that gave rise
to these uh
the kind of art that they had.
Ayush Singh says, "India for the longest
ti- time was the richest civilization.
What factors contributed to it becoming
such a prosperous land? What was the
economic model at the time? Was it
export-driven, consumption-based, or
anything that isn't prevalent today?
What are the factors that contributed to
India's prosperity? First of all,
incredibly
incredibly uh rich
incredibly fertile land.
Huge landmass. Subcontinent-size
landmass.
Um
temperate
and and good climate that can sustain
humans. Not freezing
weather that will kill people who are
weak. Not horrifically horrifically hot
climate that like Somalia or something
where no one can survive.
Decent climate. Good climate. Depending
on where you are in the subcontinent.
And very fertile soil.
Which can sustain population of
millions, today billions, right?
There is that. Then you had um
then you had Indian culture and
civilization which was
um
which was very
progressive, you could say. It It
allowed all kinds of questioning. It was
very technology-focused, which is why
you had uh the urbanization and complete
industrialization of India about 5,
6,000 years before today.
That is one factor that that gave rise
to you know, that led to the prosperity.
Then you had the
the fact that um
our kings our emperors they had good
strategies for
enriching the country.
For example, if you look at different
empires, they had different uh they they
solved like I said for different
strategic problems. The Cholas, which
are a much more recent empire, they
controlled the maritime trade between
between um the subcontinent and the
east, which made them fabulously
wealthy. The Kushan Empire and the Gupta
Empire also, they controlled large parts
of of Central Asia, which once again um
gave them you know,
gave them tremendous amounts of of uh of
wealth in terms of revenue
because of the trade which they
controlled between India the
subcontinent and the west, which is
Europe and uh
Mesopotamia and Egypt and so on
through the land route as well as the
sea route.
Uh so
the economy was
to some extent export-based.
Whatever the Europeans wanted Indian
spices, Indian textiles uh
whatever else they wanted, we exported
to the Europeans and we got gold in
exchange. Similarly with the people of
Mesopotamia and the people of Egypt, we
were trading.
And uh
so to that extent we were export-driven.
To
for all intents and purposes, we were
consumption-driven. Our own
society, which was so large, our own
population, which was so large, was the
consumer of whatever we produced.
And we imported very little from the
west. Maybe some luxury items like lapis
lazuli or whatever we may have done, but
mostly it was gold in exchange for uh
for whatever the Europeans wanted, which
was mainly spices.
Um
what was the economic model to
Different periods of time you had
different economic models. Sometimes you
would have had uh
free economy.
Sometimes you would have a centrally
controlled economy like during the
Mauryan time the Ashokan time.
Um the Kushan economy was
to some extent centrally
um
organized, but it had different elements
of different things.
It was more of an export-import-driven
and kind of a middleman-like economy to
some extent and so on.
So, different parts different periods of
time you had different models.
And they all worked
as long as the
administration is good and as long as
the emperor or the imperial system knows
what they're doing, it will work fine.
So, different periods of time, different
systems, different models, different
approaches, different strategic
approaches, different tactical
approaches, but they all worked in their
respective contexts.
Feminist Slayer says, "What's the origin
of slavery and was it practiced
universally across societies or
primarily within Abrahamic cultures?"
And Sum- Sumit Aggarwal says, "Who
invented slavery? Was it the Turks or
the Europeans?"
I would say that slavery has existed
since before recorded history.
I'm I would imagine slavery has always
existed as long as humans existed.
And it definitely is older than recorded
history.
The Turks and the Europeans, they simply
were continuing traditions that were
age-old, age-old traditions, extremely
ancient traditions. Like I mentioned
just a while ago, the Scythians
one of their principal sources of
revenue was the slave trade.
The Scythians.
I would say many of us in India would
have some Scythian ancestry by now.
Yeah, well, they they were into slave
trade and they they
they It was a very lucrative lucrative
trade.
So, um
and the Scythians came before the Turks
or the Europeans. The Scythians were
around like 5,000 BC.
Um at least 3,000 BC.
So, what's the origin of slavery? The
origin of slavery is
the origin of humanity.
See, the world has always been the kind
of world that if you are weak, someone's
going to take advantage of you.
If you're going to If you're going to be
weak, they're going to take your lunch,
they're going to take your wallet,
they're going to take your family,
they'll take your land, they'll take
everything.
They'll take you as well.
That's See, the human species is a
very violent species.
That's been our history. All major
change in human history has happened
through warfare. And with warfare there
used to come slavery.
So, the Turks and Europeans were simply
continuing the old traditions. Nothing
that they invented.
Now, was it Was slavery practiced
universally across societies or
primarily within Abrahamic cultures? The
Abrahamic cultures are recent, like
3,000 BC 3 3,000 years before today.
1,000 BC is where the Abrahamic culture
starts. Give or take a couple of
centuries, maybe, right?
Slavery is way before It It It existed
way before the Abrahamic cultures.
Um
so what's Where was this practiced? Was
it practiced universally across the
world? Look, let's look around.
The Abrahamic cultures very slavish.
They
They were very fond of slavery. No
question about it.
The
it was there during the Abrahamic times.
If you look at Egyptian civilization, of
course they had slaves.
They practiced they practiced slavery.
The Romans, of course they practiced
slavery.
The Greeks, oh yes, they very much
practiced slavery. The Chinese, of
course they had slaves.
Various African African cultures, of
course they had slavery. Um the United
States was founded on genocide and
slavery
and theft of land. So, the United
States, slavery yes. England, of course
they had slavery.
Around what?
Around 1,000 AD at least minimum 10% of
the people in England, they wore these
copper collars, which they could not
take off ever. Even after they died,
they were buried with copper collars.
Those were slaves.
You had slavery. The Vikings
they had slaves. All across Europe you
had slaves. The Romani people were
frequently enslaved and massacred.
The Turks, of course they had slaves.
The Arabs, of course they had slaves.
The Chinese, of course they had slaves.
The Greeks had slaves. Who Who is left?
The Persians?
Persians probably also had slaves.
Probably.
Who did not have slavery? We Indians did
not have slavery. Now, if you ask
Google, if you ask Wikipedia or
whatever, they will say Indians also
practiced slavery. Why? Because the word
dasa means slave.
The word dasa does not mean slave, it
means servant. A servant is not a slave.
If I say my name is Ram Das, does it
mean I'm I'm Rama's slave? No, I'm
Rama's servant.
Right?
But there are these scholars.
Well, let's Google. Let's Google some
scholarly works, shall we?
Um
slavery in ancient India
ancient India India
uh Pramod
Pramod Kumar or something Pramod
something
UGC some See, UGC is a
huge problem.
UGC
Pramod Kumar Pramod Kumar 1 second.
The quality of this this lit of this
research that comes out of Indian
universities is horrific. Look at the
quality of this research. Who is this
imbecile Pramod Kumar? Slavery in
ancient India
Shudra slavery rights of slaves Look.
Standard missionary atrocity literature.
Indians are the most slave-minded people
today.
Indo-Aryans settled in northwest Who is
this utter imbecile Pramod Kumar?
This is the problem. Indians are so
mentally colonized. Indians have this
gigantic inferiority complex. And the
quality of research that comes out of
India's universities, it is abysmal.
And the government of India
instead of reforming this, they're
encouraging this further.
Anyway, my point is slavery never
existed in Indian culture in Indian
civilization. It existed everywhere
else.
And that's the deal.
Okay. Uh Amisha says, "Why didn't
Alexander the Great go west and conquer
Rome? Why did he focus on going east all
the way to India?" Well, multiple
reasons. First of all, Rome
We saw the map will I'll not open the
map once again. Rome is west of Greece
across the Adriatic.
But, at that time during Alexander's
time, Rome was the struggling little
city.
They did not even have control over
even half of Italy present-day Italy.
It was a struggling insignificant
uh obscure little city.
No one cared. There was no wealth there.
There was nothing to There was nothing
of any of any value in Rome.
And west of Greece were the lands of the
barbarians.
The Europeans were essentially
what?
Wearing animal skins and eating raw meat
at the time. The Greeks were the
civilized Europeans, if you could call
them European, right?
So, that's one reason. There was nothing
of value in Rome. Why go west? What's
the point?
Secondly
Alexander's father Philip
Philip of Macedon was a great man.
And his great uh
ambition was to conquer Persia and take
revenge for ancient Persian humiliation
of Greece.
So, Philip of Macedon had already made
plans, raised an army, done all the
preparation for an invasion of Persia,
which is east of Greece.
Persia was the old enemy. Persia always
fought the Greeks and the Romans and
always went west. They never fought
India.
So,
the Greeks wanted to take revenge on the
Persians. Alexander's father Philip
wanted to take revenge on Persia.
And obviously cover himself in glory
personal glory. But, Philip mysteriously
got assassinated in front of Alexander
and his and his mom.
Okay? And then Alexander at the
at the age of 16 or something becomes
the king of of Macedon Macedonia.
So, he takes this forward. He takes his
father's plan forward. That okay, my dad
is dead. I will go ahead and conquer
Persia.
And Alexander's
tutor was Aristotle.
So, Aristotle was requested by Philip to
tutor Alexander.
And he had taught
taught Alexander told Alexander about
the riches of India and India is the
greatest of the eastern civilizations
and so so and so forth.
So, Alexander dreamed of going to the
ends of the world and conquering India.
And And Alexander had this demon inside
him.
He had to prove to himself and to the
rest of the world that he was greater
than his father.
He had this rivalry with his father even
after his father was dead.
So, that's why he decided that he will
go west to eastwards and conquer Persia
and then India. So, he was able to
conquer Persia. On the way, he was able
to conquer Egypt as well.
And he did he did all kinds of
atrocities on the way.
That's a different story. And then he
reached the outskirts of India and there
was a disaster.
So, that's the reason why Alexander
focused on going eastwards instead of
westwards.
Because See, first of all because Persia
defeating Persia represented
revenge
it represented glory. But, Persia was
also fabulously wealthy.
And after Alexander defeated Persia, he
took all the gold all the wealth all the
silver everything of value out of Persia
and beggarized Persia.
And he intended to do the the same thing
with India as well.
Didn't quite work out that way.
Rushab Shah says, "Why did it take so
long for the US to capture Osama bin
Laden? Why does the US forgive Pakistan
even though bin Laden was found there?"
Okay, we'll treat this as a historical
question because it's about 25 years
ago, so kind of historical.
Uh why did the US take so long to
capture bin Laden? Maybe they did not
want to capture him.
Maybe maybe they wanted to capture him
at a later point in time when it was
more appropriate
more opportune time to do that.
Yeah?
You always need periodic times of
success and victory. So, keep that for
later.
We already won
um you know, we already
uh conquered Afghanistan.
So, let Osama go now and after a decade
we'll capture him.
Or whatever. We never we never saw any
evidence of the capture and and killing
of Osama, but that's what we are asked
to believe.
So, um that's one reason. I don't really
know the details because these are all
still classified matters. Now, why does
the why does the US keep on forgiving
Pakistan?
Pakistan is an is an American asset.
They do what the Americans tell them.
Sometimes they do some naughty stuff,
but it's okay. As long as the asset is
valuable and useful, Pakistan will be on
good ground.
Yeah, so we So, Osama bin Laden was
found in Pakistan. Apparently, he was
found right outside the Pakistani
military academy in Kakul.
Or wherever it was. Abot- What?
Abbottabad.
Right outside the Pakistani military
academy.
And yet no action is taken against
Pakistan.
Very strange, isn't it? Very mysterious.
Let me
Shall I?
Why not?
You can ask this question about the US,
right?
Why does the US keep forgiving Pakistan?
You know, Israel
Israel has this track record
of going after anybody
who has killed a Jew or hurt Jewish
interests.
When there was the Munich Olympics
massacre Munich Olympic massacre, the
Mossad went after each and every
perpetrator of the of the massacre and
eliminated each and every one of them.
They went after the Nazis for decades
after the Second World War was over
and took out Nazis from various parts of
the world.
They brought Eichmann back from
Argentina and hanged him.
Yeah, we know that. So, why hasn't the
why hasn't the Mossad gone after
Lashkar-e-Taiba?
Who did 26/11?
You have to ask questions.
Right? You should.
Amisha says, "How do you How would you
Who would you define as Arabic people?
Are are Palestinians, Egyptians,
Syrians, Lebanese, Moroccans
are all these people considered to be
Arabs or only people from the Gulf are
considered to be true Arabs?"
I think there's no real definition
today. All these people speak the Arabic
language and they're part of the Arabic
world or Islamic world.
If you ask an Egyptian person today,
they do consider themselves to be Arabs.
They consider themselves to be part of
the Arabic world.
So, from their perspective, they're
Arabs.
I suppose from the perspective of the
people of Tunisia or Morocco
they may not consider themselves to be
Arabs. They may consider themselves to
be Berbers.
And the word Berber is the Arabic word
for barbarian, by the way.
Yeah, so that's a very nasty word, but
that's the word they use for themselves
today, the people of North Africa.
Libya, Morocco, Tunisia,
Algeria
So, people the people of North Africa,
barring Egypt, probably would not
consider themselves to be Arabs. They
perhaps the Libyans consider themselves
to be Arabs.
But, if when it comes to Egypt, Syria
I'm sure most civilized I mean Sorry,
most educated Syrians don't consider
themselves to be Arabs because the
Syrians have never been Arabs. They are
an occupied and and
uh subjugated people.
The uh Syrians. Lebanon, they were never
really Arabs, but today they speak
Arabic.
So, it all depends on how you see
things. From my perspective,
uh the Arabic people are the people
who live in the Arabian Peninsula.
Which is Saudi Arabia, Oman, Qatar
Bahrain
perhaps Yemen perhaps you could
uh and and the UAE etc. Yeah?
I don't consider the Iraqi people to be
Arabs.
They are the descendants of the
Mesopotamians.
The Assyrians and the Akkadians and the
Sumerians and so on.
But, today they would consider
themselves to be Arabs. So, it's it's
kind of
mixed bag.
If you are a purist, you would say that
the only the people of the Arabian
Peninsula are are Arabs. But if you look
at it from linguistic and etc.
perspective, then there's so many more
Arabs.
Okay, there's many more questions, but
we are about to reach the 2-hour mark.
Um what should I do? Okay.
Tanmay Deshpande says the philosopher
Euhemerus
suggested that gods like Zeus might
actually have been deified rulers from
the past. What if Zeus was once a
powerful king whose deeds were magnified
in religion? Zeus's attributes, supreme
authority, control over the sky and
thunder call real-world monarchs who
claimed divine right. Also, his name
shares roots with Dyaus Pitṛ.
The Vedic sky father god as we know. In
my opinion, I feel the same for our
history and philosophy as well regarding
Shri Ram, Shri Krishna, etc.
What are my thoughts?
So look, many gods are deified kings of
the past. Shri Ram, Shri Krishna, we
know are historical figures. I mean, the
Europeans would laugh would say we are
with a joke, but no.
Shri Krishna, Shri Ram are historical
figures from our history. And they they
have been deified as gods. And they are
considered to be considered to be
avatars of
of
Vishnu, right?
What about Indra?
Isn't it possible that Indra,
who is a Vedic
god, the the the the most powerful of
the Vedic gods, it's possible he may
have also have been a king in the past.
Long before the Vedic age, maybe a
thousand years before the Vedic age,
maybe 2,000 years before the Vedic age.
Maybe it's an ancient ancestor king
who did such incredible feats that he
was then deified and turned into a god.
It's very much possible.
When it comes to Zeus, he is um
the the god of thunder, right? The god
of the thunderbolt. That is nothing but
Indra.
Zeus is the Greek version of Indra, but
the name comes from Dyaus Pitṛ.
Dyaus Pitṛ, Zeus Pater, Jupiter.
And what's the weapon? The thunderbolt
and the hammer Mjolnir. Oh, that's the
that's Thor. Again, the same god.
So
Zeus, his two weapons are the
thunderbolt and the hammer.
Indra has a single weapon called the
Vajra, which is a hammer as well as a
thunderbolt.
And Indra, if you look at his story, he
defeats a gigantic evil
serpent or dragon or sea monster called
Vritra, right?
And he smites Vritra with his Vajra.
So if you look at
Zeus,
he defeats a great sea monster with his
thunderbolt.
Jupiter defeats another sea sea monster
with a thunderbolt. So does So does
Thor. It's the same god all over again.
So when it comes to Zeus, they've taken
the attributes of Indra, but they've
taken the name of Dyaus Pitṛ.
And that's the deal. So it's possible it
it would have been a deified king. It's
it's very possible, entirely possible.
Okay.
Let's take some questions now from the
live chat because I still have more
questions I could have taken, but I'll
take a few questions for the next few
minutes from the live chat. In case you
have questions,
please do ask in the live chat. I'll
take a few right now.
Uh is he reading live questions? Yes,
sir, I am reading live questions.
Atif Hussain says Zeus is Kubera. Kubera
is the king of the Yakshas.
The Yakshas are guardian deities. They
guard treasures.
And they perform some other
uh functions as well in the divine
world.
But Zeus is not Kubera. Zeus is the
personification of Lord Indra with the
name of Lord Indra's father, which is
Dyaus Pitṛ.
Okay, um um um um um um Rajarshi Gon
says,
"Were North, South, Northeast Indians
followers of Vedas and Sanatan? If yes,
how did they develop such distinct
languages? Will they Why did they
diverge? Or is it the other way around?
Were they unified later? They were
unified later.
Okay? The Vedic culture, it it was
associated with the Bharatas,
with the Bharata clan,
the clan of king
Divodasa and his son king Sudas. King
Sudas was a great man. He stood alone
against a coalition, a confederation of
more than 10 clans who came together to
fight him. And he defeated them all with
the help of Lord Indra.
And then
in victory,
the first thing after victory is he
expelled all those who stand stood
against him. He expelled them out of
India. They went into permanent exile.
And they gave rise to the Indo-European
languages in
west of India.
And then
whoever was left in India, he said,
"Okay,
the deed is done. We have I have won.
But now you're all welcome to join me.
And I have my set of gods, Indra and so
on and so forth. And we uh give
offerings to our gods through the medium
of Agni, who's also the who's also a
god, a messenger of the gods. And he
said that you all can also join in
the Yagna.
And your gods are also welcome at the at
the at the in the Yagna. So when we
offer
ghee and whatever else to Agni as an
offering to Indra, etc., we are also
going to offer it to your gods. We are
all together now.
And that's how everybody came together.
That was the first grand unification of
India.
Yeah? That's the origin of Indian
civilization.
So
originally, you would have had lots of
different belief systems and all that
in India. But eventually, because of the
victory of King Sudas,
everything was unified slowly,
gradually, etc.
All right. Okay.
Thomas says, "Can we consider the
Kushans to be Can we consider the
Kushans and the Sakas to be Indians?"
See, today
I'll I'll first take the today's
question, then
the question of the time period you're
referring to.
Today, a lot of people, if not the
majority of people in northern and
western India, including Gandhara,
including Pakistan, including Gujarat,
Rajasthan, Maharashtra,
I don't know about Maharashtra, but at
least western and northern India,
Punjab, Haryana, etc., Kashmir,
all these people
will have a little bit some extent some
some
fractional Greek ancestry, Kushan
ancestry, Shaka ancestry, all that.
So it's there in us.
Now, when it comes to the Scythians, the
Sakas,
were they Indians? Well, they invaded
India 2,300 roughly years ago.
Okay?
And why why did they have to invade
India? Because they were fleeing from
the Kushans.
Why were they fleeing from the Kushans?
Because the Kushans were fleeing from
the Huns.
That sort of thing. The Scythians were
most likely descendants
of one of the losing clans or multiple
losing clans of the Battle of the 10
Kings, which happened God knows how many
thousands thousands of years ago.
So they were expelled out of India. They
set up They set up kingdoms in Central
Asia.
And some of them became nomadic.
Okay?
And they
they lived all across Central Asia,
which was which was called Scythia.
And about 2,300 years ago, they
re-entered India.
And when they re-entered India, they
were able to conquer parts of India.
They ruled over those parts of India.
And was there any cultural clash?
Was there any ethnic clash between the
Scythians and the and the Indians?
Nothing.
They still had the same culture. Their
languages were still similar.
The Scythians were sun worshipers.
Saurashtra, Saurashtra,
the rashtra of the sun.
Yeah? Who ruled over Saurashtra? The
Mahakshatrapas,
the Western Satraps, who were Scythians.
They were the lords and protectors of
the great Jyotirlinga of Somnath, and
they controlled India's trade with Rome.
So the Scythians, the the Sakas,
they were of mixed ethnicity by the time
they re-entered India.
Some of them would have looked white
also with blonde eyes blonde hair and
blue eyes, but originally they were they
were of Indian origin. Same goes for the
Kushanas. Okay? The Kushanas, they were
found in the Tarim Basin region, the
Tarim River Basin region. If you go to
that region today, you will find
mummified remains of these their
ancestors, the Tocharian people, the
Tushara people, whose language was
similar to Indian languages,
whose script was kind of
it went ka kha ga gha. Ka kha ga gha all
that stuff, right? And their genetics
were R1a, which is again very similar to
our genetics.
Even though some of them had blonde hair
and red hair and blue eyes.
So they were all of Indian ancestry.
Okay. Now, next, what else?
Lavanya says, "Any progress on the
Dwarka Island excavation or any more
sites of Saraswati Sindhu in Bharat?" I
have absolutely no idea.
I heard that there was some further uh
marine archaeological
uh expedition that happened recently
in Dwarka, off the coast of of modern
Dwarka, but I'm not sure what the
outcome is. I don't know what they're
trying to achieve.
What whether there is any real progress
or not, I have not seen any significant
progress in the past 30 40 years. So
I've no idea. No idea. Maybe something
is happening, maybe I'm not informed,
but I have seen nothing
of any significance happening. So no, I
don't know.
Any more sites of Saraswati Sindhu in
Bharat? We have thousands, but nothing
is being done there.
Yeah?
Nothing is being done.
Soumyajan asks a good question. What
about the die dice game?
In which Draupadi is to become dasa?
dasi
How could one become servant through
gambling? You know, in every culture
the culture may have norms, but there
are some idiots who flout the norms,
right?
Why were the Kauravas
deserving of being exterminated?
Because they were adharmis.
Because they treated women like that.
And
would you blame only the Kauravas for
this? Would you not blame the great
Yudhishthira
for not having any self-control? He knew
that his cousins, the Kauravas, were
adharmis.
And how can you bet your family members
like they're objects?
So, you see in every culture, you will
have some idiots, some low-quality,
low-standard people who will do bad
things.
Who was Kansa?
He was
the mama, the maternal uncle of Shri
Krishna. But he was a monster, wasn't
he?
But these are the exceptions. They are
not the norm. In our culture, these
things are not acceptable. And that's
why it was a good thing that the
Kauravas were exterminated. Do you
understand? There are always exceptions
to the rule.
You have to understand. You cannot
because there is one exception somewhere
that doesn't mean we are evil.
We destroyed the Kauravas because they
were evil. And that's how we upheld
dharma. That's what our culture says.
Please understand. There will always be
exceptions. There will always be
exceptions.
Okay. Oh, it looks like there are some
super chats. Good god, super chats.
Please don't take any more super chats.
I need to end the live stream, but I
will finish the super chats for sure.
Krishna says, "Why did USSR give up
military bases in Beijing?" Because
after the Sino-Soviet Soviet split
the Chinese were no longer willing
to accommodate these bases. You see?
After the Ussuri River crashed clashes
and after the Soviets decided to nuke
China, which the Americans prevented
them from doing. So, that's why they had
to give it up.
James says, "L'Afrique a toujours été
pauvre.
Ils vivaient dans des huttes de terre
jusqu'à ce que les Français vous offrent
la civilisation et les ampoules
électriques." He's saying the Africans
have always been poor. Mhm? They live in
these little huts, you know,
until the French came and offered them
civilization and electricity and all
that.
Look, we don't really know the history
of Africa.
The history of Africa that we know has
been written by the whites, by the
Europeans, after they destroyed Africa.
And Africa has been so badly
impoverished
that the overwhelming majority of
African countries don't even have
an archaeology department. So, we don't
know what the past was like.
So, the Europeans came in, they
destroyed Africa, they pauperized
Africa, they genocided Africa.
They destroyed the indigenous culture.
Uh let me show you something.
Permettez-moi
de vous montrer cette chose.
Okay,
Africa religious demographics
map.
Map. Let's take a look at the religious
demographics of of Africa.
Um Hinduism must be Mauritius.
Do you have anything native left in
Africa? This is the deal with Africa.
Look at this.
This is what they've done. They've
destroyed all of African culture,
everything that was indigenous to
Africa.
Totally destroyed it. They proceeded to
write Africa's history to paint the
Africans as barbarians.
And they introduced these brutal foreign
religions to Africa, which causes so
much bloodshed in Africa. And then they
say that you know what, we civilized
Africa, we brought in electricity, we
brought in whatever, but they look at
the Africans, they're still not raising
their standards.
You caused this. You destroyed Africa.
You installed dictators. You installed
corrupt people to rule Africa, which
perpetuates the colonization. And then
you say that Africans aren't capable of
ruling themselves.
You starved Africans so that the IQ
drops 30 points, and then you say that
Africans are the lowest IQ people in the
world.
I can't do that.
Please.
And the same arguments have been used
against the Native Americans
in in North America.
Anantha Subramanian says, "How to
listen? We are discussing history today,
not geopolitics. We will not discuss
geopolitics today. Tomorrow Tomorrow is
geopolitics day, okay?
Uh favorite king or emperor? I don't
have any one favorite king or emperor.
Ashoka is one of my favorites. Okay,
even though he was slightly naughty.
Kanishka, definitely one of my
favorites. Shri Chinggis Khan,
definitely.
Among the Europeans, maybe
Julius Caesar, yeah.
He was not a king, he wasn't not an
emperor, but one of my favorites. And of
course,
probably
um
William the Bastard,
who came to be known as William the
Conqueror. And his son, Henry the First.
And there's more. ICMB says, "Can you
tell me the story about the Kosovo war?"
Very convoluted. I can't explain right
now.
Very convoluted. Balkan history, my god.
If I want to untangle that, it'll take
me a minimum 1 hour.
Balkan history, the roots of this
nonsense goes back goes goes back to the
Ottoman occupation. Even before that,
you need to understand Slavic history.
Very convoluted. I can't explain right
now. Impossible. Impossible. I mean, I
wish
I could. It's very complicated.
I apologize. Can't do it.
Not when I'm ending the live stream. Uh
Dilute H2O says, "We told the word Hindu
originates from Persian Sindhu."
The Persians used the word Hindu
because the Persians had lost the
ability to say the word say the say the
sound sa.
So, instead of sa, they used ha.
So, Sindhu became Hindu.
Sindhu is a is a is a Sanskrit word that
means river, actually.
Yeah? Uh Brihaspati Agam says, "Land
between Himalayas and Samudra is
Hindustan."
Brihaspati would Agam would no
pre-Islamic or pre-Turkic text would use
the word Hindustan.
Let me just try and corroborate what
you're saying. Okay, let's go to Google.
Brihaspati Agam
Bri
Brihaspati
uh
Agama
Okay?
Really?
Wow.
There are so many ancient texts. I am
not aware of this at all. The word
Himalayan
Samarabhya
Yavad
Yavad Din
Hindustanam
Okay, what is the Brihaspati Agam?
Brihaspati, is it a real thing?
Agama Brihaspati
Look, I don't even know what the
Brihaspati Agam is. Okay, I'm not aware
of this.
Does it really exist, the Brihaspati
Agama?
What's the origin? Uh
original text
Do you have it?
It's not definitely known.
It has undergone revisions over time.
Surviving versions may not be original.
So, look, this is not this is not
something that you can, you know, rely
upon. This this claim
that it it talks about Hindustan.
No.
From my little brief research that I did
did over the past 60 seconds, it's clear
that it's not something that is reliably
attested.
Okay?
The point is the word Hindu
it originates from Persia.
The Persians looked upon their eastern
neighbors, and the the land started from
the river Sindhu.
And the Persians could not say Sindhu,
so they said Hindu. And that's how other
the Arabs, who eventually conquered
Persia, they started using that term as
the term for the people.
And then they said sthan. So, Hindustan.
That's how the word Hindustan came into
being.
Deva has become new a new member. Thank
you very much, Deva. Appreciate that.
Ut Yo says, "History of Tuvans. They are
classified as a Turkic based on
Turkic based on language,
but genetics show them closer to
Mongols. What's your opinion? Do you
know Shoigu?"
Shoigu Gerasimov
Shoigu is half the one.
Look.
Are they Turks? Are they Mongols?
First of all, the Turks and the Mongols
also share the same origin.
Understand that.
The Turks are descendants of the of the
ethnic group called the Huns.
The Huns are descendants
are the same people as the Xiongnu, who
emerged out of the region called
Mongolia 2 and 1/2 thousand years ago.
The Huns emerged out of that region,
which is now called Mongolia.
They displaced
the Kushara people
the Kushans westwards. The Kushans
started fleeing the Huns.
Because the Kushans started fleeing
westwards, the Scythians who were living
westwards, they started fleeing
southwards and invaded India
to flee the Kushans, who were more
powerful.
Then a couple of centuries later, the
Kushans invaded India to flee the Huns,
who were more powerful.
The Huns eventually became the Turks.
And the Huns and the Mongols were the
same people. What's the Mongol language
word for human? Hunnu.
Hun.
So the two ones are classified as Turkic
but genetically they're the Mongols.
It's the same thing.
Same thing.
Essentially.
Amisha says, "How did the development of
bipedalism
influence the evolution of childbirth
and infant dependency?
Did walking upright make make childbirth
more difficult?" I have absolutely no
idea Amisha ji. I have no idea about
this matter. I have never researched
this.
It's possible. Look, when you adopt a
bipedal gait from a quadrupedal gait the
your skeletal structure will change. Um
your femur your your
tibia they will elongate and change in
shape. The pelvis changes in shape.
Um the lumbar spine all of that changes.
So maybe
the pelvis becomes more narrow. I'm not
I'm not sure how it works.
Gorillas have far wider pelvises than
humans.
Uh it's possible that it may have
influenced the evolution of childbirth
and infant dependency.
Maybe it could possibly have made
childbirth more difficult but I am not
100% sure.
It certainly would have changed the
skeletal structure which can certainly
affect the way things
happen mechanically at least. But I
haven't studied this in detail. So I
won't be able to tell you right now off
the off off the cuff
whether it did indeed have this effect.
Indian Soccer Player says, "Punjabi So
Pakistani Punjabis boast about Arabic
and Turkish Turkish ancestry but they
speak Punjabi and have Punjabi last
names. What are my thoughts?"
Slave mindset.
Right? Slave mindset. Inferiority
complex.
The Pakistanis
they identify themselves based on what
they are not or what they claim to be
not. Their identity is that we are not
Indians.
We are not Hindus.
That is their identity.
So then what are you? Oh, maybe we are
this maybe we are that.
See?
If you go to Turkey
and you take away for example
hypothetically completely, okay? This is
a thought experiment. If you take out
the religion from Turkey, what is left?
Turkish culture Turkish Turkish
language, right? They're still Turkish.
If you go to Egypt
and you take away the religion they kind
of become Egyptians again. Right?
Their language is still Arabic but they
kind of become Egyptians.
Uh
if you go to Persia Iran you take away
the religion
suddenly they become Persians again.
You go to Pakistan you take away the
religion, what will happen to them?
They'll become Hindus and Indians again,
right? But they don't want to be that.
That's why they claim all kinds of
different ancestries. Sometimes Arabic
sometimes Turkish. Now I don't know what
else they can do. What Chinese now? What
will you do? Neither the Arabs nor the
Turks want you.
They speak Punjabi and have Punjabi last
names. It's it's slave mentality. It's
it's sad to see. It's sad to see but it
is what it is.
Okay peoples, I am done with the
questions for today. Thank you very much
for all the questions. I really
appreciate all the questions you asked
and it was great fun
fielding all the questions.
Thank you very Oh, there's one more
super chat apparently.
Uh please clip James. Africans would
appreciate. Certainly, I will clip all
the questions. Yeah, they will all come
out on the channel
in due time.
So people, thank you so much for your
questions. I really really enjoyed this.
And tomorrow I look forward to seeing
you and doing a geopolitics live stream
super chat live stream.
And yep, I'll see you tomorrow. Keep
learning. Keep asking questions. Keep
raising your standards.
And I shall see you tomorrow. Take care.
Thank you very much. Until tomorrow.
Bye-bye.